Alright, beautiful people's welcome to the last video of this specific section.
In this section, we will basically going to see that how you can upload any Android application
to the Google Play Store.
This is going to be the entire goal of this application of this specific video.
Perfect.
So, first thing which is mandatory that you need is a Google Play Console account.
So, for using the Google Play Console account you need to pay around 25 dollars for the
lifetime.
So, basically you pay once and you can upload as many apps you need.
Someone got it?
This is something that you basically need.
First thing you need a Google Play Console account and you have to verify yourself.
They will ask you some basic information.
like your name, your email, your some of the maybe your some driving license, some PEN
card, maybe bank statement just to verify you.
Okay, that's it.
And within a week, they will actually going to verify you and then you need a 14 testers
as well.
They can be your family, they can be your friends, you can actually share that app with
them and they can just they just need to download that app.
That's it.
Okay, these are some basic steps that you need to do.
These are the prerequisites that you need.
Alright, so now I have basically prepared some basic, I can say that testing some basic
notes for you.
Initially, we will going to see that how you can publish your app to the Google Play Store.
So everything to prepare before and while publishing an Android app to Google Play.
including graphic sizes, privacy policy, tester emails and how to share without collecting
emails.
So, two different testing paths we need we can actually follow.
First is we can going we can use let me show you that okay first thing what you need you
need account and one time setup we know that we basically need to do this and then what
you need.
Second thing is very important.
Second thing that you need is your storing the listing text like your app name, short
description of your app and full description of your app.
Okay, let's just do everything one by one.
So step number one simply visit towards your Google Play Store app and then simply press
on create app.
So the moment you press on create app first thing they will ask you is your application
name.
unitapp, you can name it anything you want.
Then second thing is the package name, so for the package name you simply need to go
inside your app.json and search for android and whatever the name of this package you
simply need to grab this.
Okay, so this is so basically second thing this is the package name you need to paste
so simple and you can actually simply run for check availability this package name is
already in use so you can simply add here the unit flow to you can name it whatever
you want and after that first thing they asking you is the default language definitely this
Next thing is you can change this in later app store definitely.
So is this your app or is this your game?
Definitely this is my app.
Simple.
Is this a free app or is this a paid app?
So this is the free section you can go for it.
Second we also have the paid one.
Okay.
But right now we have the free.
Next thing they are asking you developer program policy you basically need to check for it
also need to check for it and then simply press on create app.
So the first step very first step is done this one I mean Google play developer account
you need to get this second you need a Google cloud project when you wanted to use EAS submit
but for now let just ignore this EAS submit we will see this later.
Then you need to basically create a create app, we already did this, we also have this
package name and done.
What next?
Next we need app name, we already have a short description and full description.
So now the moment you press there you will find something like this thing, but now you
will see that you have bunch of tasks to do.
Look at that, you have these much of tasks to follow.
First is some privacy policy you need to set, then some sign in details you need to give,
then you need to give ads, content rating, target audience, data safety, government app,
in features that you have.
And then health in same way in which category your app will actually come then you will
basically going to set up your store listing.
So these are all of the basic information that you have to do.
Like if I just simply press on set privacy policy so what you need to do basically you
basically need to create one privacy policy.
How you can create?
You can, you must own one website that website actually contain the privacy policy page.
You can simply paste the link of that specific privacy policy app.
Okay.
I don't know right now I have any or not.
I need to basically search for it.
sample privacy policy website for India and I can just search for anything and then I
can simply select on live edit maybe download for words.
and download PDF and then these are something your privacy policy you can publish this online
and share with anyone you wanted to share.
Okay let me just simply put this simply press on save like this is kind of my privacy policy.
In the same way next we need to add the sign in data.
So is any party or application restricted?
For now no.
So I can simply save this and I can come back out of it.
Nice.
So the second step is also done.
Third step is your app support any kind of ad?
For now no.
No my app does not contain any kind of ad.
So, again I can simply press on save simple very easy.
Then I can again come back.
Next thing they're asking you your content rating.
So, you need to do so this receive rating for your app from official rating authorities.
Complete the content rating questionnaire question eyes and to receive official content
rating for your app.
Ratings are displayed on Google Play to help user identify whether your app is suitable
for them or not.
Then just keep giving the answer what is the email address, email address let me just put
my sample email.
Next which category is your app is definitely all other types and terms and conditions let
me just agree.
Next, does the app contain any rating relevant related to any violence, any languages and
whatever is that any some specific gender downloaded as part of the app package.
So code or assets, so right now I can say simply no.
User content sharing, does the app natively allow user to interact or exchange contact?
No.
Online content?
Promote or sale for age restricted?
No.
Malleus miscellaneous does the app share the user current and precise physical location?
Does the app allow your user to purchase digital?
No, I think everything will be no for now.
You can just read according to your need and press yes on the debates.
Then I can again save this like from where I'm getting save options at the bottom of
it.
Got it?
Then what I can do?
Then I can simply press on next.
Next, these are the ratings I got perfect and then I can simply press over it.
Now I get my ratings as well and cool amazing after that target audience.
So my target audience is from anyone can use our applications.
I think 6 to 18 and over.
Because they already got introduced to unit conversion.
So they can use our app as well.
And now like legal and regulatory compliance, you need to check it.
You have declared that your app does not contain ad.
If this is incorrect, no, my app does not contain simply press next.
Teacher approved program.
You have team up with teachers and children education and media specialist to spotlight
the best app for kid on Google Play.
In the teacher approved program, expert rate app for quality and age appropriates, learn
more about include my app in teacher for now does not include anything simply save this
and let's just move ahead.
Alright, and now I can once again go to my dashboard and after that next data safety,
you just have to just fill this long, long, long form, take so much of time.
simply press next does your app collect and share no no additional badges simply press save save
let's just come back next is government app is your app developer or any behalf of government no
Let's just come back once again.
Next is financial features.
Select of the financial feature your app provide.
Nothing.
I mean, we, yes, my app does not provide any financial features for now.
Then I can simply press on save and I just wanted to stay here.
Definitely.
Yeah, I can go, I mean, next, I can go back, cool and all good.
Next is two declaration need attention.
First is advertising.
Why this impact?
All developer required to submit the declaration of this app.
Does your app use advertising ID?
No.
Let's go back.
Next declaration that is have health apps.
Start declaration.
No, my app does not have any health features.
This is just a very simple app, but now you got the gist that what are all the features,
what are all the things that you have to go through.
Okay.
Then let me go back once again.
All the actions are done.
Everything is cool.
Perfect.
So now what we can do now, I can simply go to my dashboard once again.
Everything is done.
Manage how your app is organized and present.
Select an app category.
Yes, I wanted to select.
So this is and the category should be how I can select my category.
Okay, I can I need to press on edit.
This is app and category should be if I am not wrong.
That is should be more of the tools because I provide bunch of tools inside this.
Let me close this tags I can even add bunch of tags like health and fitness sports business
tools because I have tools I have you know I don't have calendar actually I think a
A clock, alarm and timer? Nope.
Driver education, emojis, events, like look at that lot of options that you actually have.
You can select for bunch of them and simply press on apply.
Next you need to add some basic information of your like your email address.
Let me put my sample email.
Next is the phone number that I just don't want it to add my phone number right now and
the website link.
So I think my website hopefully my website does not got down for now.
Okay.
I need to fix this.
I'll fix that later.
But for now, let me put my website name simply press on save.
And let me close this, this is fine, nice.
Let me once again go to my dashboard, all of this thing is done, set up your store listing,
this is very important.
Now first thing you need your app name, second thing you need the 80 characters for your
short description of your app, in same way you also need the full description of your
app under 4000 characters.
Fast Offline Unit Converter, so this is the short description that I can have, ok, this
is fine I think and in same way I can have the full description.
Now for the graphics your app icon must be 512 by 512 pixel, for the feature graphics
you must have 1024 by 500 and for the phone screenshots you need minimum.
2 screenshot and maximum of 8 screenshot and for the adapted icon foreground you need 1024
to 2024 image and for adaptive icon background you need this and monochrome with this.
Optionals, but useful.
You can also add table screenshots, promo videos, TV banners, wear operating systems
and quick design tips and use same color as your app screenshots, feature graphics and
icon.
And for the app content, make sure you have policy program there.
And these are the bunch of things you need to create a put inside your privacy policy.
And this is your privacy policy is required and all good.
This is what basically you need.
We have already added all of this information.
Then what you will get now, you know after that, after everything going to happen, what
you can do right now, you can simply put save as draft.
Next, thing that you will get is your store listing experiments.
So they will ask you for to create your store list.
You can put the experiment name store settings.
Okay, now this is found, this is fine, this is also fine.
I think now this is the high time simply press on test and release and after that you can
And simply press on.
All of this thing is done I think.
So yes this is the only thing we basically need to add.
So after all of this information adding what you need to do simply press on test and release
and after that simply press on testing and right now I wanted to go for close testing.
Then simply press on close testing after pressing on this is mandatory if you are uploading
your app for the first time in 2026 simply press on create track you can name it close
testing track.
And after that what you need to do now you basically need to select the country like
in which countries you wanted to run this test.
So simply select all of them simply press on save in same way releases is fine.
Now who are all your testers?
So I have a few internal testers you can actually create your email list and add them and then
simply press on save.
After that what you can do you can simply press on create a new release and this will
actually going to create a new release for you.
So the moment you press on new release now they are asking you to upload the app bundle.
Now how you will get this app bundle?
So for getting your app bundle what you need to do you need to create a production bid.
So, you basically need to run this specific command for EAS let me show you that you can
simply run EAS build hyphen hyphen profile.
Now profile should be production very important and then platform right now we are specifically
us in android so the platform should be android.
So, the moment you run this application, this command, so after running this command what
you will actually going to get, let me show you that.
Let me take you towards the EAS build that we have.
Ok, so let me just search for my this builds.
And let me open this for my unit flow.
So where is this?
This is the unit flow that I have and build.
But right now I need my production build.
So I can simply press on production build and after that you will get this download
option.
So, simply download this production build and interestingly you will see the format
of this download build is.aab very important and simply go to your app store and upload
this specific build that you have.
This is your app, this is your optimized version of your app, you basically need to upload
this, alright, so this will take few minutes, let's just wait for installation of it, just
uploadation of it.
Alright guys, so uploading is finished, now what you need to do, you need to basically
put the file.
The name of the release you wanted to add, so this is so you can identify this release
and it is this not going to show the users on Google play.
We suggest a name based on the first app bundle or APK in this release, but you can edit it.
So I can name it as unit flow bundle.
Alright, and okay now there's one problem actually, now they are saying me that your
package name should be matched, it's okay your package name should actually going to
match, I just intensely change the name of it, you can even add some release note and
then simply press on next, so the moment you press on next, now what will going to happen,
Okay, now you need to upload APK Android bundle for this app, you need to app cannot published
yet complete the step in the dashboard again you just need to complete all of the steps
like set up your store listing these are all the information you need to upload and that
is the last update you need to do and share this with your internal user and wait for
14 days after 14 days you will automatically going to get this options let me show you
that this option apply access to production that's it.
And now within a week, within a week or two, this application will automatically live on
Play Store.
So these are all the steps you actually need to follow for uploading your, I can say that
apps to Android application.
Same thing will actually going to happen with the icons these are the complete full publishing
checklist you need to follow.
So make sure to take screenshots of this otherwise I'll make it public and you can even visit
to this specific website link alright.
So these are the link that we have let me show you hopefully you are able to see.
So this is the link that we have so you can copy this specific link and visit here cool.
So, first thing you need a Google developer account and you need a place to console package
name should be finalized production A, B you actually need this then these are bunch store
listing assets that you need to keep ready your policy legal should be ready testing
should be also done and you can also automate that but this is optional and ignore it for
now need not to worry about and then just start uploading it.
And in same thing will actually going to happen for Apple App Store.
So for Apple App Store you basically need a Apple developer account that is around $100
for each year.
Yes.
And then look at that $99 here you can actually just go and purchase your own.
account from here, you can basically sign up for it and then you basically need a new
app.
You need a bundle ID from where you will get this bundle ID.
You can simply go inside your app, Jason.
Inside this app, Jason, you can open this icon and at this point you will search for
something known as.
Bundle ID, Bundle identifier actually and this bundle identifier is something which
is specific to your iOS application when you need SKU very simple same steps nothing you
need app name, subtitle, promotional text, description, keyword everything is completely
mentioned all the graphics you need all the other things that you basically need everything
is completely mentioned here just read it once everything smoothly going to happen for
you.
And after submitting all of the information you just need to wait again for few days a
week.
Apple sometime take two weeks, sometime takes three weeks, maybe more than that, but depends.
Alright, so these are the entire flow you need to follow and with this I can simply
say I can end this entire section.
One thing which is left is es submit and for now we can completely negate this because
this is not so much important for now.
Perfect, because for the first time you need to upload your application manually.
So that is why I have completely skipped this.
You can read more about it, simple steps you need to follow.
But right now that is not that important.
We'll obviously upload in more upcoming videos because this is the course that we.
going to maintain it for a very longer period of time.
Then in next release we will upload some good projects and some other updates as well.
Okay, so with this let me end this entire course and see you next time.