Alright everyone and welcome to one more new chapter. In this chapter we are going to talk
about Xiroscope. Right now we are done with this so let me just mark this as a green.
Now let's move ahead and start talking about Xiroscope. Now what is this? And I am 100%
sure you have listened about PUBG and inside the PUBG you are getting an option to enable
your Xiroscope.
Yes, so what is this basically? So, this sensors measure how quickly the device is rotating.
So, how quickly your device is rotating around.
ROTA, sorry, around different axis, x axis, y axis, z axis.
So we can say this is basically used for spinning motions and why it matters?
Rotation data help to create a responsive experience.
where turning or twisting the phone should affect the UI like that is the requirement
whenever you have so you can use this gyroscope.
Look what is the real world use case for it?
Let's say you are creating a steering in a racing game.
Perfect, you are creating a steering in a racing game and in same way you are doing
something for camera rotation control.
Yes, in that case you can also use it like you are creating something, a rotating 3D object
with natural gestures.
So in that case, you can also use this gyroscope.
So let's move on and we'll see.
how we can use it cool so for that let's move ahead and simply create a rotation
indicator perfect I can simply say rota tion rotation indicator dot t s x r n
fes rota
Alright, now let me just simply save it, grab it and we don't need it because we are done
with this accelerometer thing.
Below this let me just import my component.
Perfect.
Nice.
And also make sure to reload it once.
So, that we can see the output here, which is showing us a rotation indicator.
Now, how you can use it?
So, simply again very simple thing, very simple output.
First of all, again I wanted to show a message here.
So, for that I will maintain a message state variable.
and this is going to be set message.
is equals to use state and I will say right now no rotation.
No rotation.
Perfect.
I don't want it to use something animation related thing otherwise I can simulate it.
But right now we are good to go.
And same thing we need a style for a container and a text.
And a simple UI just to wrap it up and showing a message.
But right now if I come into here we are able to see no rotation.
But if I move ahead and then simply again say use effect and this use effect is going
to have empty dependency.
Perfect.
Same thing.
Let's subscribe to event.
But right now we wanted to use gyroscope.
We don't have it.
So let me import that first.
So this is the gyroscope that we have and then I can simply add event listener here.
Again we have access off right now X, Y and Z not X.
Perfect.
And inside this, what we can do again for just go for absolute value of x axis.
So math dot absolute value for z is greater than 0.5.
Then what we wanted to do, we wanted to show set a message as spinning as P I N N I N G.
Otherwise, set a message as no spinning and then I will remove the subscription.
So for that I can simply say this.
Now if I save it you will see no rotation but if I rotate my phone look at that if I
move my phone you will see that right now I am able to see spinning. I can
simulate in much better way like by showing here a rotation indicator and
the moment I'm rotating in which direction we are rotating it we can also
simulate that. Alright so let's move ahead and try to enhance this example a
bit more.
So, right now instead of showing message, let's move ahead and show a progress here.
Perfect.
So, the first thing is this and remove this use effect.
We don't need it and let me grab bunch of UI that I wanted to show here.
Perfect.
And then I basically wanted to show rotate your phone and then we are showing the progress like how much you rotated it
Perfect. So if I just save it right now, you will see something like this cool
So this is basically rotate your phone and a bar and the percentage
And as I keep rotating my phone, like every time I rotate my phone, I will increase the
value and then you will see a progress bar here.
Perfect kind of.
We'll see that how I can simulate it.
So right now what I can do, I can get a use effect once again and empty dependency.
And for Xero scope, I can show this cool.
And inside this what I can do like there's a lot of methods inside the Xero scope.
But right now let me use one more which is Xero scope dot set update interval like in
how many milliseconds I wanted to update it.
And then let me just again subscribe to event listener.
So gyroscope dot add listener and then we are going to have a Z index.
What I will do rotation amount.
So whatever the Z index value, I will multiply this by two.
So we are increasing it every time something like basic maths.
Don't get confused yourself by this calculations.
You can just write with me and you're mean.
Agenda behind this entire chapter is to understand about Xeroscopes.
That's all you need to understand.
Cool.
Right now we are just doing simulations so that you can see a visual output of it.
So now we have a rotation amount which is basically equal to maths.absolute value again
let's whatever the z index multiply by 2.
So this means we are small increasing it.
small, increase and then just simply use the set progress method.
Then whatever the previous value we have, I can get for a next.
So whatever the previous value, add there the rotation amount.
And then return here next if is greater than 100.
Then return us 100 otherwise return our next value.
Cool.
And let's move ahead and then simply add it.
Now if I save it everything is fine.
Let me just try to reload it once so that we'll see is this going to work or not.
Alright, so this is Zyroscope given number when a phone rotates we take that number and
add it to the progress.
So more rotation more progress.
Look at that.
I am rotating my phone and as I rotating my phone 360 degree you will see this has become
entire 100% and if I rerotate my phone like look at that how beautifully we have did it.
Nice. Perfect. Nice. Like, let me show you that if you don't trust me, I mean you can.
Perfect. So let me just simulate this for you. Although you don't need it, but again, we
can do. We have to show you that. So just give me a minute and I'll show you that.
Alright, so I hope so guys you are able to see this right now and look at that as I rotate
my phone look at that look at the value now if I just completely rotate it you will see
the value become now 100 yes so this is how we are basically calculating this and I hope
you are loving it cool.
Perfect, so now we are successfully able to simulate all of that.
Like right now here we are basically, again let me explain you once again, xero scope
give us a number like this z axis.
So when the phone rotates, whenever my phone is rotate.
we take that number alright and then multiply this by 2 and add that inside this progress
perfect.
The more rotation and the values become more.
So this is again there is no formula, no time stamp, nothing.
This is a very very very simple example of this.
So you rotate your phone, number will come and we are just adding this inside a progress.
Perfect.
And you can also set this on zero.
Like below this, you can have a button and that button is basically going to show you
the reset.
Perfect.
And you can reset that once again.
So title should be, let me just try to explain you.
Title should be reset and then on press what you will do, you can simply call this and
do set progress as zero.
Perfect.
So if I remove it, like look at that.
And if I just simply press on reset, we are able to reset.
Cool.
Nice.
So, yes, this is pretty much it for our chapter number two and see you next time.