Alright everyone, welcome to One More New Chapter.
In this chapter we are going to talk about Expo Audio.
So how you can basically tackle audios inside your Expo application.
Perfect.
So Expo Audio is a cross-platform audio library for accessing the native audio capabilities
of the device.
Note that audio automatically stops if headphones, Bluetooth, audio devices are disconnected.
Perfect.
So for installation, you can just simply copy this and install it.
I have already installed it, but let me first of all rerun my application and install it
once again.
So this is going to be Banex, Expo, install, Expo Audio.
Perfect.
And for using it, what you will do, you will just come down and this is how you can use
it.
Let's say you wanted to play some
So, for that I have already grabbed here asset with the name of Hello MP3.
Perfect.
So, if you wanted to place this audio inside your app, so what you will do, let's say let
me go to my screen and simply create an audio screen.tsx, rn, fes and then I can simply say
Perfect and let me save it.
Let me go to my index and instead of this I will use my audio screen.
Perfect.
Nice and if I just reload it just to update this and you will see a audio screen here.
Nice.
So for using it let me just simply coming to here.
and import it perfect I will just copying it and paste here nice so you will see first
of all we are importing the audio source so for importing it don't import like this because
I need to go one step back so double dot slash assets and inside this I have hello dot mp3
Perfect and change their naming to basically something else.
So perfect.
So now let me just come into here and instead of app I will just change their name to audio
screen.
Perfect.
And yes, now you will see that they are giving us two options.
One is play sound.
And I think sound is playing.
I don't know you guys are able to listen that or not because I have off to my system sound.
But yes, let me just, I don't know you are able to listen it or not.
But yes, this is working perfectly fine.
And in same way I can replay it.
We can have a multiple options for stopping it out.
Like let's say you will see.
We have on press play to seek and in same way I can have a stop as well.
So I can definitely search for it.
Look at that.
This is just for audio.
Maybe I can just copy this perfect paste this.
And let me simply say stop and then I can say this as I don't know how I can stop it
just we have stop I don't know this will work or not but if I just reloaded once.
Let me just save it and let me just reload it.
So after I reload it, you will see my sound will stop.
Perfect.
So this is how you can play your sound and this is how you can basically replay your
song.
Perfect.
So I think I think I have I got that idea.
What you can do instead of play, we can have a pause.
Yes, I'm searching for stop.
But like we have a play in same way.
We have a pause.
Yes, look at that.
And then I can simply say PAUSP, pause sound.
Perfect.
I can play from here.
Yes, sound is playing into my head.
I don't know you guys are able to listen it or not because I have off to my system sound.
I can pause it.
And yes, my sound is paused now.
Perfect.
So this is how you can basically control and listen to any sound.
But let's say right now you wanted to record something.
So, how you can do so that?
So, for that we also have a recording sounds option.
So, these are bunch of hooks that we have and you can just simply let me copy this perfect.
So, let me just copy this coming to here and let me paste the same.
And let me import my alert component from react native and if I save it, they are going
to ask me for a permission if I just click on start recording.
And I have already given the permission and you will see, I don't know you are able to
see that or not a simple green dot here, look at that they are showing us this microphone
simple.
This means my microphone is on and whatever I am saying here, this is recording perfect.
and I can definitely stop the recording as well.
So let's try to break it down.
All right, so you will see that I have
audio module recording presets, set audio mode sync.
These are recorders.
Perfect, we have initialized this
and in what way you wanted to record your video,
these are bunch of settings.
Like you want high quality videos,
you want low quality videos.
This is how you have an entire control over it.
Perfect and this is for asking permissions and from here you can definitely record it.
Perfect.
But now let's say you wanted to save your recording.
So for that you need to use something known as expo file media.
But for using that you need to create an Android and iOS build.
Then only you have a complete permission to access the local file system of your device.
So, that's why I'm not saving anywhere and not be able to grab that.
For that I have to do a lot of lengthy procedures.
But right now, I just don't want it to get into ES builds thing.
We'll cover that, don't worry.
But right now, this is how you can access your camera.
You can access your audio.
Right now, I'm going to go ahead and do the same.
If you wanted to use media, then you need to create iOS and Android build.
But I think this is not the right time for covering that.
But I think we have an image picker.
So you can definitely use the image picker thing.
So from here, you will basically pick the images from your like look at that something
like this from your devices.
So you can definitely give it a try.
a very simple way of using it, ask for a permission and then this is how you can launch your libraries
and access that and show that image onto this.
Perfect.
So, yes, this is pretty much it for this chapter where we have covered about recording sounds,
playing the sounds definitely and you can read more about it, read more about settings
Perfect. So this is the end of our audio chapter and see you next time.