Hey everyone, welcome to one more new lecture. In this lecture we are going to talk about
the essential core components. These components are used in almost every mobile app. So, once
you understand them building UI in react native become much easier.
So, into this lecture we are we will going to cover view, text, image, text input, pressable,
scroll view and style sheet.
This is not a component, but this is a very good utility to use for styling your all the
other components perfect.
So, let's start one by one first of all let's move ahead and start talking about view.
So, what is view?
View is the most basic layout component perfect in react native you can think of view as a
container perfect view means container like we have div so this is your view we use view
for grouping your component for creating layouts and applying we can say spacing and styling.
So if I just simply move ahead and let me just quickly set this up and I'll be right
back.
Alright guys, so for setting it up, I'm definitely going to move ahead and I'm going to go ahead
simply going to create a module to inside this module to let me open this and open in
terminal and simply code dot.
So now this is going to create open this let me close all the other files and I think yes
we are good to go.
Now before doing anything first step is going to be same simply run bunX.
Create Expo app at the latest.
So this is going to be your command to install a Expo application.
Perfect.
So you can simply just hit enter.
So this is now asking you what is your app name.
So I just wanted to be inside the current working directory.
So,./ now this is going to install all the dependencies that we have.
So, let me wait for it and then we can start developing it.
Alright, so now we have successfully installed our project is ready.
So, what is the next step?
Next step is always going to reset your project.
Perfect, you need not to touch anything.
First of all, always reset your project.
scripts/resad-reset-project.
So this is going to be reset and no.
So now you will see we are reset.
Simply clear everything and then you can run sorry, now you can run bunnex-expo-start.
This is going to start the development server of your app.
Now let me wait for it.
I wanted to open in Android.
If you are using this, you can simply scan this and open.
Let me simply press a.
Now you will see the hello world.
I hope so you guys able to see that.
Yes.
Now first of all let me unload this cool.
Now everything is fine.
Perfect.
Nice.
Now let me go to my app and index.tsx and inside this we wanted to understand first of all
about view.
What is the view?
View is used to group your component.
Now let me just remove everything and make sure that you have installed a react native
component.
So, first of all let me snooze this and Rnfes.
So this is going to write a react native functional component export for you and let me stick
with this.
Let me just simply write here the index and here a simple react component.
This is how you create.
I hope this thing is clear.
Now, if I just save it and just once again reload it just to see you need not to reload
every time and here you will see that they are showing us the index.
So inside the view and view wrap the other component it does not show text by itself.
So for showing text you have to use this text.
Perfect.
say inside this view I wanted to have the.
another view. Perfect. So let me just simply write here and inside this like if I just
try to write here hello world something like this and if I save it you will see error.
Error is text string must be rendered within a text component. So you need to copy this
once again you need to paste it.
And then you need to write Hello World here and then you need to save and this is how
you will be able to see this.
So it is mainly used for layouting purpose.
Perfect.
Now let's move ahead and talk about text.
So text is used to display text on the screen.
Important rule.
Make sure to keep that in mind.
All text must be inside this text component.
Perfect.
Yes, you need to do that.
For example, that I have already shown you here.
Perfect.
Now, let's move ahead and start talking about like we are done with view.
So I'm just keep checking it.
Let me just simply add check.
this one and yes and in same way we are also done with this so let me check this now let's
move ahead and start talking about image component so how you can basically use this image component
so for now let me comment this out.
Perfect.
And let me import my image component.
So for that you can simply import image from react native and inside this below this I
am simply going to use this.
Yes, this is going to be a self-closing component.
And they accept bunch of props but for now let me just simply write here the source and
inside the source they accept an object which have a URI and inside this URI you can show
the URL of the image you wanted to render here.
So let's say let me write here the URL like we have a HTTPS, React Native, Dev and Image
Tiny logo.
Then, you also need to write here the style.
Yes, just give me a minute style and open this inside this style.
Let me write the width of 100 and height of 100 and if I save it, look at that and you
can even add the padding.
Let's say padding of 24 if I add and save it.
and maybe padding top.
All right.
They are not working because definitely there is always a way of doing it.
But for now, let me just stick with width and height.
Perfect.
So, you will see this is how you can render the images inside it.
Make sense?
Very easy.
So, source tell yes, if I just talk about the source, source tells a react native where
the image come from.
Simple.
And width and height are required.
Without size, image wouldn't appear.
So, make sure to keep that in mind.
You have to specify the height of your image.
Cool.
No problem.
Now, let's move ahead and start talking about this text input component.
So, how you can use that?
So very simple, you can simply come into here and import your text input.
This text input is basically used for forms, login screen, search bar, I mean you know
that.
So, below this make sure you are inside the view and you can simply import text and let
me simply write text input and inside this I can simply pass bunch of props.
So, the first prop is going to be placeholder.
Let me simply write.
Enter your name and if I save it, you can see that we have a text input.
Perfect.
And in same way, I can style it as much as I want.
So I can simply going to write here the style.
Not like this.
And inside the style I can add the border width.
Yes you make sure that you are writing style in this way.
We have border width then we have padding.
Perfect and padding let's say of 10.
And boom look at that you can write the text inside this and if I just simply press if
you are on phone then definitely going to open the phones keyboard.
So I hope so that makes sense now.
Perfect. I hope no problem into this very basic, very easy to understand. So placeholder,
show hint text, you guys know about it. Then we have style, style, add border and spacing.
So we have added a basic border and the padding just for spacing.
So, text input is a controlled input will handle state later whenever in future when
we are going to use here the hooks the all the other things then you will see how you
can handle that as well perfect no problem nice.
Now let's move ahead and start talking about this pressable now this is something new.
What is this pressable? If I just simply coming to the documentation development make sure
you are on component. So, if I just simply press on pressable. So, pressable is a core
component wrapper that can detect various stages of press interaction on any of its
defined children.
So, this is simple pressable and we do not have on click, we have on press, so make sure
to keep that in mind.
How it work?
On an element wrapped by pressable, like you can create any element act as a pressable,
you can use that on text, on view, on anything else that we take, text area if you wanted
to, but alright you got the point.
We have on press in, on press out, on press in is called when a press is activated and
in same way when this is deactivated.
So they have I mean look at that how beautifully they have explained you that.
Press in.
Press out and then you can even on press.
In same way if you press for 500 milliseconds then that event comes inside on long press.
So you can do bunch of other logic on long press as well.
Perfect.
And they have even added you this.
Fingers are not the most precise instrument and it is common for user to accidentally
activate the wrong element or miss the activation area.
To help a pressable has an optional hit right you can all right you can ignore it for now
you need not to understand anything for it.
So yes now let's move ahead and start using it.
So how you can use it you can see that this is the press me so the moment you press and
press 2x 3x cool but let's move ahead and start using it.
So how you can use it very easy.
I can just simply coming to here and import the pressable component and alright values
never used cool let's move ahead and start using it so below the input I am going to
use the pressable and inside the pressable I am going to have the text component.
And what just happened?
All right.
I think let me import my text as well.
Perfect.
What they are saying?
Unknown property pressable.
Why we have that?
Let me just search for pressable.
It's fine, maybe this is some different issue, but no problem.
This will going to work.
And if I just simply search for event on press and then if I run a simple callback here and
let me just simply use the alert.
Yes, we have alert as well.
And if I just simply say button pressed and if I save it and inside the text, I can simply
Click me and save it.
Perfect.
Let me try.
Is this going to work or not?
And if I just simply click this and boom, look at that.
We have a button pressed.
So all right, this is basically coming because I am using extension on spell check something.
So I'll go into disable that in upcoming lectures.
But for now, you can see the moment you click this.
And this is how they are showing and again, this is not the best UI design that we are
creating.
We are going to create crazy UIs.
Don't worry about that.
But for now, we are only understanding the logic of it.
In same way, we also have a scroll view.
So what is the scroll view?
Like let me simply come into here and import scroll view.
Scroll view is basically used.
Let me tell you always make sure that the scroll view at the top of it.
Perfect, instead of view you can use a scroll view.
So let me just instead of calling this view, let me use the scroll view and save it.
Scroll view is basically used to render a lot of items at once to create this scrollable
screen.
Perfect.
Let me just try to add a lot of texts here like below this.
Let me add a lot of text.
Let me save it.
Perfect.
Like only we have only this much.
You can simply add a lot more, lot more.
Let me just checking this out.
Perfect.
And you can look at that.
You can simply scroll this and this is how you can simulate the scrolling view.
Perfect.
So I hope so that makes sense now.
So scroll view, render all the element at once.
Good for small content for large list.
Like when you have lot of text, you definitely not going to use in this way.
We definitely have something better out of it.
So, there is something known as flat list component.
We are going to talk about that in upcoming lectures.
So, these are the some core components 90 percent of the time you are going to use them
not 90 80 percent of time you are going to use this 20 percent components cool.
We have in same way we have button as well if I just simply import here the button.
And let's say below the image, if I just simply use the button and button will not work the
way you expect.
Like let me show you how.
Where is button?
Let me go back.
And yes, we have UI interface button.
So button will work something like this.
So let me copy the code of it.
Let me try to paste that.
Perfect.
And we don't have anything for now.
So I can simply again write alert and simply say anything and boom, look at that.
We have just added a color of it.
We have a title.
We have a lot of other things as well.
So the moment I click over it and we are showing the alert.
And you can even see this is a native specific UI.
If you are on iOS, they are showing you a different kind of alert.
So that is the beauty of it.
Perfect.
Nice.
Only last thing that we are left with and we have lot of text.
So let me try to remove them because we don't need it.
from here till here perfect let me format this once and perfect.
Now let's move ahead and start talking about something known as style sheet.
So let me import the style sheet component and this style sheet is basically using for
styling your component.
So how you can initialize a style sheet?
Where you are exporting default this out of it inside it depend, but let me just simply
write here const style and then you can simply use the style sheet component and then we
have a method known as create and yes now inside this you can write the object name
like in HTML CSS we are writing the class names here you will write the object name
something like let us say let me write the container.
container have the padding of 20.
Perfect.
And in same way, let me add simply a comma.
Let me add a text.
Text is going to have a font size, let's say of 18, not 28, 18.
And color is going to be blue.
Simple.
Let me save it.
Nothing is going to change.
Now if I move ahead and let me try to show you that.
Let's say onto this text and simply write here the style and inside this style I can
say always say this styles perfect instead of styles you can simply say this as a styles
dot now we have two design one is for container another one is for text so let me simply write
text and the moment I save it boom look at that.
Perfect.
You can even use the font weight and you can add the font weight, let's say of 800.
And if I just save it, you can see this become bold.
Now, if I just make it red and save it, you can even add hex RGB, a lot of other things
as well.
Perfect.
So, and in same way, you can use this for containers.
Let me try to create one.
Let me copy this below this text.
Let me paste this.
Perfect.
So let me import view from react native, save this and boom, this is your container.
This one and in same way, we have this style text here.
So yeah, pretty amazing.
You are writing your mobile application in just two to three lectures, which is crazy.
So, yeah this is pretty much it for this lecture and see you next time.