Alright everyone, welcome to one more new chapter. In this chapter we are basically going to talk about
markers in much more depth. Perfect. So basically we are again going to create a simple mini project
that is map camera plus markers.
So, the main feature is again displaying the map which we already have and showing the
multiple markers and move camera to mark on a button tap we can say that and marker properties
have coordinates, titles, snippets, dragable we see that how we basically implement it.
Got it again for that I have again prepared a simple.
array, so this array have a coordinates and then titles and then snippets and then draggable
as true perfect.
So for title Delhi snippet capital of India a lot of same Mumbai and then Bangalore and
how you can basically use it.
And again, let me just point out one more thing which is expo map still is in alpha
and they definitely required a development build.
So, make sure that you have a development build then and only you are testing it out
cool.
So, for testing this out what I can do I can again go to this UI settings below this we
can have a marker this markers have markers Google.
And, if I save it and decrease the size of it look at that, this is the three locations
that we are on and you can see this is somewhere around Delhi, this is somewhere around Mumbai
and this is somewhere around, yes this is somewhere around we can say.
Bangload. Alright, this is pretty amazing. So basically, render marker define this marker
data, this is how we have added and each marker, yes, each marker have this much of property.
The coordinates and if you definitely press over it, you can see something like this.
Got it again, you can get the proper Google map is not installed or is disabled. It's
And you can definitely click them.
I do not know they are not dragging some, but you can definitely drag them as well.
Yes, look at that.
This is how you can drag the entire, let us say let me paste it somewhere around.
So they have some different location on the basis of that we can fetch that and show that
specific location.
as well. Perfect. So when the draggable is true, so the moment you just pick it up and
drag it somewhere wherever you basically wanted to put this out. Got it. Nice. Now let's move
ahead and yes, this is how you can basically add markers inside your application. So yes,
this is pretty much it for this shifter and see you next time.