Hey everyone and welcome to one more new lecture and today we are diving into something super
powerful named as linking API in expo.
This is chapter 2 of our device and system APIs module and trust me after this lecture
you will be able to open URLs, handles, deep links and send emails, make phone calls and
even integrate URL schemes like a pro.
So, let's jump right in perfect.
So, first of all, what do you mean by linking API?
So, the linking API allow you your app to open external URL.
All right.
So, if I just simply say what is linking API?
So, the first thing is.
Open external APIs. Second, handle deep link. They are using just to handle deep links like
URLs that open your app. Perfect. Have you ever used any shopping application like Amazon,
like something else?
So, the moment someone share that product link with you and you click over it, you are
redirected to the app to the same product got it.
So, how they are basically working, they are working with the help of deep links.
Then we have let us say you wanted to send emails and SMS messages, then and only also
needed.
Sometimes you receive a notification and the moment you click on this notification, you
are redirected to that specific page from where that notification for that notification
was generated, got it.
So you need it.
like you wanted to make phone calls.
You wanted to open other apps like map, WhatsApp, etc.
And whenever you wanted to parse your URL parameters and wanted to handle navigation,
in all of that case, you need a linking API.
So think of it as a bridge between your app and the outside world.
Why do we even need the linking API?
So let's again, let's take the scenario one.
You are making a e-commerce app.
So whenever let's say user click on customer support, we want user to open their email.
Whenever user share any product.
Yes, this is what I'm talking about.
Whenever users share any product, so they can basically share the dialogue and the moment
you click over it, they are redirected to that specific product page.
Whenever you wanted to track your orders, so we can say you need it like open external
tracking URLs in that case you need it.
Whenever you wanted to call your customer care services, then let's say you are creating
a social media application.
Let's say you just simply here and creating a social media app, then user click a link
in bio and then we are opening the browser.
Perfect.
So user click link in bio.
And then we basically opens the browser second whenever you open the Instagram.
So how they are basically launches that is the main thing that we have a share button
which open the native share sheet will see that how you can create your own share sheets
will see that.
In same way, we have a forward delivery app.
So in forward delivery app, you basically can able to get directions like just to open
the Google map.
Perfect.
So we can simply say open Google maps.
You can call restaurant.
You have a payment link.
This is very important.
So opens.
We can say a payment app.
So all of this scenario is only possible with the, one of the reason this is only possible
with the help of linking APIs.
Perfect.
So without linking API, your app would be isolated.
You can say that.
And there is no way to interact with other apps or we can say URLs for it.
So, let us see that how we can basically implement that.
So for that, there is one library for it, name as expo-linking, an API that provide methods
to create and open deep link universally.
So simply copy this and just give me a minute.
Let me fix it as well and let me open.
My VS code alright and let just open one PowerShell and simply hit burn x expo install
expo linking alright.
So in 200 milliseconds we have successfully done it.
Now let me go to my app and index, we do not need this index details for now, nice.
So let us take the example number one and that example is basically going to be used
for we can say opening the URL and let us say just to make some sort of call.
Let us see how you can basically.
So, basically let me go inside this and let me name this as linking link so that we have
and what I can do, I can create one folder and it's fine let's just organize them into
the link and you can simply again say.
basic linking dot tsx rafce and basic linking. Let me save it. Let us copy this. Let us
go to index and below this, let us grab the basic linking component.
So, how you can basically make this basic linking even without config callback div.
Oh, what just happened?
Sorry, my mistake.
R and FES.
Then this is basic linking.
Let me save it.
Now we are able to see it.
Perfect.
So, first of all, let me import all of the things that I need.
So, I have just basically imported linking from expo linking.
easy. So, first of all let's create one utility that will help us to open a website. So, I
can simply say const open a website is equals to a simple async function no problem and
then what I will do I can let's say take one URL. So, for now I can simply take Google
urls/sttp/lens.
Google.com and we can check if URL can be open or not.
So for that we have some utilities.
I can simply say can open is equals to await and then I can say linking and they we have
one function name as can open URL and then we pass the URL inside this.
Then this can open can return a true and false.
If this is true.
Then simply say linking dot open URL and then simply pass the URL that we have otherwise
simply go inside else and then we can show the alert.
All right, so this is we have alert and alert dot alert and then simply say error.
We can simply...
What I will say I can simply say cannot open this URL.
Let's see how we can use it.
So for using that let me go to my view perfect first of all let me paste all the UI that
I need.
So, let me just copy this and let me paste it cool and then inside the view first thing
that I need I can simply say style and this style is going to be a styles.container and
initially I can simply show here the linking examples.
And below this I can have one name as touchable opacity.
This touchable opacity is going to show us a text.
That text is basically saying open website and then what I will do I can simply say on
press.
Yes, whenever I press I wanted to call my open website function easy, simple.
And then let me pass all the styles that we have easy now let me save it and the moment
I click on open website you will see we are redirected towards the Google.com perfect
nice in same way let's say instead of this I wanted to take
Oh, what just happened to my personal site.
So I can simply say www.surechkumarjha.me.
Hopefully this is the right URL.
I don't know.
Let me go back and if I again press on open website.
So what just happened?
I am not redirected.
Let me try to reload it once, maybe this will work right now and alright this is still loading
and if I again press on open website and yes look at that.
Now I am redirected to my personal portfolio site, cool?
So this is how they basically look to us, cool?
Nice.
So this is the first utility.
Now let's say you wanted to open your WhatsApp, you wanted to open your maps.
So how you can do, you wanted to send some SMS to someone else.
So let me just keep adding the example for all of them.
Same thing, same utility, open URL.
You just need to know that how you can create URLs for that.
Let's say whenever you wanted to send SMS to someone else.
Got it.
So first thing you need a phone number, second thing is the message and for iOS definitely
you need to go through this and for Android this is how you need to go with it and simple
whenever you say send SMS you can send SMS.
Let's say I wanted to open a maps.
So how you can open a map?
Whatever the location address you wanted to pass here and the URL and whatever the address
the moment you click over it you are redirected to that specific location.
I am not clicking here.
I just wanted to don't show my location for now and in same way whenever you wanted to
open WhatsApp Instagram same thing you just need to know.
something like let's say this is someone's phone number, you wanted to send this hello
message and simply say URL and this is the WhatsApp and can open, we are just understanding
about this and can open thing, cool.
And we can implement all of the utilities that we have, cool.
So you can definitely give it a try that how you can implement that.
nice and if I save it, so you will in same way like only we have for now in same way
you can even send emails you can send whatever you want cool.
So let me for now comment this out and.
Why it is not reloading in real time?
There is something wrong in it, it's fine.
So now we have sent SMS, open maps, open WhatsApp and all of is going to show here and the moment
I click any of the button, they will be redirecting us towards that specific
page. Alright, so now you guys can see that this is what actually showing to us and again
the moment you click any one of them you are redirected to that specific URL. Perfect, so
this is the basics of linking. Now let's go one step ahead and start learning about something
known as deep linking receiving URL.
So, for that let me just go to this link and create one component name as deeplinking.tsx
and then RNFES and this is going to be deeplinkinj linking perfect.
And let's let's start again from basics.
So first of all, let me import all of the things that I need just to simulate this.
And after this, what I will do, I can simply initialize two state variables, initial URL
and received URL.
Perfect.
And then what I will do, I can simply run a use effect here.
So, that use effect will something like simply say use effect call this callback add empty
array and then say linking yes linking dot get initial URL yes this is how you can get
your initial URL like get the URL that open the app if if binary chance you have opened
and then we have a then then inside this we have access of URLs.
perfect. And then what you can do inside this simply move ahead and say if we have any URL
for it then simply say set initial URL equal to the URL and then in future in a while I
am going to create here a function name as handle deep link. Then listen for URL while
app is running so I can simply say const subscription is equals to
So, linking dot add event listener and that event listener is URL then listen for that
specific event perfect and then you can definitely console that out whatever the URL event is
coming and at the end we wanted to clean this up.
So, this is how we will clean it up.
So, let us move ahead and this is such a big function, you again need not to get too much
depth into it.
So, let me just try to paste it down entirely, cool.
And let us try to understand what is going on here, perfect.
So, first of all, let me just simply say here any, cool.
So, we have a handle deep link method that will be used inside this you can simply pass
the handle deep link method and in same way for the URL first of all so handle deep link
URL.
So, this deep link is going to first of all accept a link and we are parsing it.
So, in parse you will see we have the scheme.
What is the scheme basically?
Scheme is we can say let's say your app name is Instagram.
So, Instagram colon slash less is the scheme for that.
Then we have hostname, then we have path, then we have query parameters.
This is the property that is available inside a deep linking object.
Then this is the received URL we are saying.
If the parse path is equals to product, get the product ID and show that.
This is just a simple simulation.
There is nothing as such which is exist for now.
We are just basically uptesting it out.
So, let us I have basically created here one URL deep link which is URL is product and then
they have query parameter of 1, 2, 3 and name of that product is cool product.
Perfect.
Let me try to first of all paste the entire URI for it.
So, let me just quite big.
And then let me try to explain you what is this going to do for us, but for now, first
of all, let me paste the entire UI again, you again need not to write anything.
You can also just bring that out and paste it.
We are just understanding about it.
Cool.
And this, this lot of.
concept that you learn while using that in a real world.
So right now I am just explaining you things in a better way so that if I save it and if
I go to my index.app, I don't need any basic linking below this if I just simply paste a
deep linking and now if I save it.
and look at that. So this is your app URL scheme. This is the URL scheme that we have basically
created. Then we have this is the URL and this is the received URL. And if you just simply
coming to your consoles, you can even see. So this is the host name. This is the path
we don't have any. There's no query perms. The scheme for our app is exposed. So these
These are basically a bunch of examples.
Just try to understand that.
The main thing is, main thing is like how you can get the initial URLs and how you can
parse that URL and after parsing it you have access of this much of properties.
That's all we wanted to understand here, cool?
So basically whenever you receive a link when app you are open, so you basically listen
to that specific link.
You can parse that, you can show the history of the received URL and you can just...
We can say you have better control over your URL.
That's why we basically using it.
Cool.
Nice.
You can see that we have one method can open.
You can even collect manifest.
There's a lot of initial URLs.
So get the URL that was used to launch the app.
If it was launched by a link, so whenever your app is launched by a link, so basically
they are saying whenever you wanted to test this out, this is how you can test it, but
for now it's fine, we need not to even test it, so we are good to go, cool.
Now let's move ahead and we'll see how we can basically create a universal link.
Perfect.
So for what do you mean by universal link?
Universal link means let's say you wanted to redirect to YouTube, Instagram, Twitter,
Facebook, Spotify, Maps.
App Store, Play Store.
So simple thing is again use the methods, scan, open URL and then redirect user to that
specific URL.
That's all you can basically do with it.
Got it?
So the important method that we need to understand inside it.
So if I just try to explain you that, cool.
So, the first method that we have is scan open URL, you just need to understand about
it.
Second is whenever you wanted to get the initial URL whenever your app or launch for the first
time, then we have one known as create URL and then parse.
These are the four method that you guys need to keep in mind for now.
easy, I hope so, perfect.
So, these are the four method that you need to keep in your mind, perfect.
So, yes, we can say that this is how you can linking your applications.
So, I wanted to take one more example.
and show you whenever you wanted to share something.
So how you can show the sharing sheet.
So for that what you can do, let's try to test that out here.
So inside the react native if I am not wrong, so we have one component name as share and
how this share is actually working.
This is pretty simple, I mean you can just simply use it cool and let me just show you
how.
So for that what we can do at the very bottom of this let's say we don't need this steps
let me just cut this out cool.
So below this I can have we can say a touchable opacity.
So, I can simply say touchable opacity, alright, thus we don't have it touchable opacity and
this touchable opacity is basically going to say the on press and on press what I wanted
to do, I wanted to create a function name as on share, cool and inside the text I can
And if I go at the top of it and at the bottom of it, if I simply create a const on share
is equals to a sync inside this a sync if I simply say share, share dot look at that
we have three things but we basically need a share and you can simply show a message
here check out this amazing
app and if I save it, let's see cool.
So where is my share button?
I don't know.
But if I just cut this down and out of it, if I show here as we have yes, the moment
I click on share, right, so I am not able to click it.
if I go at the top of it and here if I pay
it nice and if I just try to simply click on share yes look at that this is how we have
opened our sharing sheet whenever you wanted to share this anywhere and this is the message
check out this amazing example you can copy this you can send somewhere you want you can
even add links of your component and this is how you can use it.
In same way with the help in we have share, we also have dismissed action, we have share
action as well and this share action have bunch of other things as well.
But for now the main thing is the share.
So, the moment you click here, you will see something like this and if you are using iOS,
you will see related to that, cool.
So, yes, this is how you can basically use expo linking.
So, these are the main functions you need to keep in mind for now.
And this is how you can open your sharing sheet as well.
So, amazing, amazing job and this is the end of chapter number 2.
See you next time.