Alright everyone and welcome to one more new chapter in this chapter we are going to see
how you can configure a development build of your expo application perfect.
So for that first of all I wanted you to simply go to the documentation.
and click here alright then you will be redirected towards the expo build so if
you read expo build we know that it's a hosted service for building app binaries
for your expo and react native projects so you can simply press on create your
first build
Got it.
And you will see the expo build allow you to build a ready to submit binary of your app
for Google Play Store or Apple App Store.
In this guide, let learn how to do that.
Alternatively, if you prefer to install the app directly to your Android device or emulator
or install in the iOS simulator, we will point out.
You, towards the resource that explain how to do that, but first thing first what you
need this is the prerequisite.
First look at that.
ESBuild is a rapidly evolving service before you set out to create a build for your project
we recommend you to consulting the limitation page and other prerequisites.
So it's fine if you wanted to go.
First thing is you need a project perfect that you want to build.
So we're going to create that in a while and then you need a expo user account.
So simply just go to export.dev/signup and make sure you are sign up and you know the
username and password for it.
All right, so I'm giving you a minute.
Just go and quickly come back.
All right.
So I'm assuming that now you have a expo user account.
as well.
Nice.
Now, let's move ahead and what I wanted you to do is to simply go inside your VS code
for now and let's initialize a new expo project.
So I can simply say Banex create expo.
I don't know what is the command.
I always forget this.
Sorry for that.
Let me go to the documentation I think yes so create expo app yes I am writing that
route create expo app at the rate latest alright and yes dot slash no problem so they are basically
going to install my application.
Alright, so now you can see that we have successfully installed it.
Now for testing this out, what we will do simply, I can simply say "Bonex expo start".
So this is basically going to start my development server, but you will notice something by default.
This is showing us using expo go.
So if I just coming to like this, just give me a minute, let me just quickly fix this
out and yes, now if I just simply press a, so this is basically going to start my expo
application and look at that they are building it.
So by default, every time whenever you create your application, they are starting inside
your expo go.
But now we know the limitation of expo go.
Yes or no?
Yes, we know that.
Now, let's move ahead and we'll see how you can first of all configure this.
Perfect.
You just simply close this.
First step is always is to configure this.
But for before configuration, you need to install bunch of things with me.
So again, go to introduction, create your first app and yes, first of all, install this.
So simply copy this.
and open new terminal and say burn add -g es cli so we are basically installing
the es cli tool no problem alright so in less than 10 seconds we have installed
the as cli
So, you can also use the above command to check if a new version of ESTheorize is available.
We encourage you to always stay up to date with the latest version of No Problem.
Now the second step is always simply run ESLogin.
No problem I can simply run ESLogin.
So, the moment you hit ES login, you can see that they are already saying me that you are
already logged in as code by Suraj.
So, do you want it to continue or no?
So, as you know, I am already logged in.
So, I can simply say no.
But.
If you just simply hit a yes login, they are going to show you some we can say URL you
can simply visit there, put your credentials and login you guys are developer you can simply
do so that no problem.
And if you also wanted to check you are logged in with which ID you can simply run yes.
Who am I?
Alright, what you will run?
You can simply run EAS, who am I?
And if I hit this, you will see this is the username which is coming.
No problem.
Alright.
Now, what next?
Next is very important.
Next they are saying you.
is to configure the project to configure an Android or an iOS.
I'm only going to focus on Android for now to configure because wider audience have Android.
That's why and this is easy to understand because iOS have a lot of we can say security
things.
So, I just don't want it to go into that for now at least to configure an Android or
an iOS project for ES build.
Run the following command.
So, if I just simply copy this and if I just paste it, es build colon configure.
So, this is basically going to start configuring my build and you will see.
ES project not configured, no problem.
Would you like to automatically create an ES project for this module 10?
Yes, I wanted to.
I can simply say yes.
Now on to my dashboard, look at that.
They are giving me a link.
HTTPS, export dev account code by Suraj projects and module 10.
If I just simply press this for you guys and open it.
You will find that ok now inside the project I have this project name as module 10 making
sense nice this is your dashboard amazing tool so which platform would you like to configure
for AIS build so no don't press on all for now let's go with android same you can go
with iOS but for now let me just simply press android.
Nice, now what they are saying, your project is ready to build nice run EIS build when
you are ready to create your first build and once the build is complete run EIS submit
to upload to app to App Store.
No, we don't want it to do that right now at least.
All right.
So if I just CLS this and again coming to here, let me go to this.
Next step after configuration for development, definitely we recommend creating a development
build and if I just simply press on development build, how to create that.
So for that you need a library known as Dev client.
So, let's install this first of all.
So, this is your expo dev client, no problem.
I can simply hit BUNX, expo install expo dev client, no problem, simple thing.
Alright, so in less than 7 seconds, we have installed it successfully.
What next?
Next is to run a build.
But.
Next thing they are saying you additional configuration may be required for some scenarios
that your app depend on environment variable not now at least is your project inside of
a monodap or not now do use private npm packages again not now.
So what is the next step?
Next step is this simply run EAS build.
platform and you can also just build for we can say profile, there's multiple profile,
let me explain you what is that.
So right now if I just simply move ahead and try to show you what has changed inside our
application.
So first thing you will find a new JSON file name as EAS build, alright, then this is basically
showing the EAS version and this is the main thing which is the build.
And build is in three profiles.
First profile is the development with development client as true.
So this means whenever you are going to install this development client inside your physical
or simulator device you are actually getting the debug version of your application.
So you can actually connect that with your metro server and whenever you make change
inside this you can see the output.
Then we have a preview, this is basically for internal distribution to your manager,
to your tester, to your team members basically and this is the production.
Production profile means you wanted to, you wanted to, you wanted to, you wanted to, you
send this application and we can say upload this application to the App Store or Play
Store.
Then we have another services like AS Summit but for now we do not need it.
Along with this you also go inside your package JSON.
And inside the package JSON, you will find something known as export dev client.
No problem.
So now we have all the things ready.
So what we have did inside this chapter, we have basically configure a development build.
All right.
This is thing, one more thing, which is very important.
If you go inside your app JSON, and if you go to the very down, yes, you will see something
new.
which is name as extra and inside this extra you will find a router which is empty and
yes they have a project ID with this name.
Alright so this project ID is basically this thing got it this is the project ID which
is configured here alright look at that we have DD83 at the end here we also had DD83
at the end.
So this is the first step.
And what is the name of this step is to how to configure a development build.
So from next shifter we are going to see how you can create the actual build and use that
into your device.
So this is pretty much it for this shifter and see you next time.