Alright everyone and welcome to one project video in this video we are going to use the
same build because I don't want it to have a lot of builds that's why and inside this
same build we are going to create here we can say reminder buddy application where we
will going to schedule a lot of remainders for us and that will going to send us a notification
in the given time.
Perfect, so without wasting any time, let's move ahead and let me go to my index.tsx and
start developing it.
So for that I need a bunch of component, perfect, so let me import all of them.
Just give me a minute, alright.
So, first thing first the thing that I need right now is let me replace here perfect.
So, I need alert a button flat list model platform scroll view style sheet text input
touchable opacity and view alright.
And after that at the top of it I wanted you to create here our interface for our reminder.
Perfect.
So, the interface contain id and the title and the message and the date make sure that
we type of date and one emoji and one notification id.
Perfect.
Then I wanted you to create one emoji options.
So, let me copy my emoji options and paste it.
So these are all the emojis that I have added here.
I have clock, medicine, gym, water, books, aim, coffee, chai, whatever you wanted to
say it and then we have here something known as moon basically night, party and study.
So these are bunch of random emojis I have taken here.
Perfect.
After that.
Add here a bunch of state variables.
So we already have token.
No problem.
I wanted to add remainders and set remainders.
Then we have model visible and show token model and then add a form state variables
which contain title, message.
and selected emoji and then one which is known as basically we can say selected minutes like
5 minutes, 3 seconds, 10 minutes, 1 hour, 2 hour, 1 day, 2 day whatever is that.
So I have basically added here selected minutes and set selected minutes is equals to use
By default, we are setting it up towards the 3 seconds.
In 3 seconds, I am going to get a notification.
Easy.
So, these are all the state variables that we need and everything we already set it up
need not to do anything for now.
One thing that you can I think we are good to go nice.
Now, what next?
Next is create a function with me.
So, simply say async function name this function as schedule reminder, reminder, reminder whatever
is that let me off my AI first of all perfect.
So, dual reminder and this schedule reminder first of all if we do not have any title perfect
we are going to create here form.
So, if you don't have any...
title basically, then I wanted to show here first of all alert, please enter a remainder
title and then return from here.
Perfect and then next open a try and catch block with me and first of all let's get a
a schedule date like on which schedule date I wanted to send.
So, I have just basically added a new date, whatever the time is happening, whatever the
selected minutes and then multiply by that 60 and then 1000.
All right.
And then let use the schedule notification utility.
So, I can simply say cons notification ID.
is=await notifications.
Then you can see that we have lot of functions.
So one of utility that I need is schedule notification async.
And then first of all they are going to accept the content.
So, content will contain these bunch of things.
So, I have a title, I have a body, a sound as true, priority which is notification.android
priority, notificationPriority.hi.
And, instead of high we can keep that to max much better.
And then we have a simple data which only contain a remainder ID for now.
And after this they have something known as trigger option.
So this is where we are basically going to tell them the type of trigger which is a time
interval we can say that in how many seconds you wanted to trigger it and do you wanted
to repeat it or not.
So, this is a simple type which is notifications.schedulable trigger input type which is type of time interval
you can see that a calendar a daily month monthly time interval we simply want a time
interval because on the basis of time 5 minutes 10 minutes I wanted to trigger my notification
making sense I hope.
Then in how many seconds you wanted to trigger it.
So simple whatever the selected minutes we have, multiply by 60.
Easy and let's initialize a new remainder after it.
So I can simply say this new remainder.
This is a simple ID, a title, a message, a date, an emoji and the notification ID which
will come from here.
Perfect.
And then what I will do, I will simply say set remainder, whatever the previous reminders
we have and the new reminders, we are spreading them, spreading all the previous reminders,
adding the new one here, making sense.
And then I can say set model visible to false.
We can simply show the alert success, remainder, schedule, and we can even show that into catch.
Let me formatted once.
This is your function, which will basically call schedule remainder function.
Okay.
In same way, we can even have a delete remainder.
So very easy.
Let me just simply paste that.
This delete remainder basically simply going to accept a text and this title on press we
wanted to cancel this schedule notification which we will get from this state variable
we will accept remainder, remainder have IDs on the basis of that ID we wanted to cancel
the schedule.
Easy and then let me add bunch of other function.
This is a reset form function in same way we can have a date related function.
You need not to understand that simple copy paste just copy and paste with me because
this is not about date and function.
We are just creating a mini project.
This is basically going to convert into hours and minutes just for UI purpose.
Alright.
Then we can even show the shorted reminders.
So, sort them in this way and upcoming reminders.
So, let me simply show that and then we can add all the time options we have.
So, let me just simply paste that out.
Cool.
And now let me copy everything.
Yes, because there's too much of code.
You again need not to write anything.
Just copy and paste the UI with me.
Alright, so first of all let me paste the entire UI and let me also paste the entire
CSS for it.
Alright and then we are good to go.
Perfect.
So what just happened?
Okay, we need to import that achievable opacity.
All right, and we also need to import the model from react native.
We also need to import the text input and the scroll view as well.
But scroll view, make sure you are going to import from react native and at the very bottom
this style sheet.
Okay, now let me save it and look at that.
This is how our application will look.
Yes, let me import my flant list as well.
Nice.
Let me try to break this down for you.
This is our entire UI.
Again, this is a simple mini project.
That's why I'm just copy and pasting it.
Got it?
So this is a view simple this like this.
This is your token.
Yes, you can copy from this token.
You can copy this.
It's completely up to you.
Now you will see right now we don't have any remainder.
So this is your header.
Simple.
They are basically showing you the token model and you can copy that token.
Easy.
Nice.
Then we have stats like how much upcoming schedule reminder we have and how many totals we have.
Then all the remainder list will show to here.
This is will this will render onto the flat list.
Nice and then we have add button and then we have models.
So this is model basically going to add for remainder.
So let me just show you how let me press it.
So the moment I press it, this is how my model will look.
You will see we have icon.
I can select.
Let's say this one.
Perfect and for title, I can simply say learn about learn expo notifications.
Perfect.
And if you wanted to, you can even add a message.
Hello buddy.
Don't doom scroll.
Insta focus on study.
Okay and then you can even set the remainder 3 seconds, 5 minutes.
Let me just go with 3 seconds.
This is the by default and let me simply say schedule.
Look at that remainder scheduled.
I can simply say okay and this is here you will see your remainder schedule and after
3 seconds we got our first push notification.
Look at that.
And if I open it, this is how this will show to us.
Learn expo notification, hello buddy, don't doom scroll, insta, focus on study.
So this is how you can create your own remainder ready application.
Perfect.
So amazing, amazing job.
And with we can even add a bunch of deep links here.
You can even search more about it, like how you can add deep links.
The moment someone send you notification, if someone click it, they will be redirected
to that specific link.
A lot of things to do.
So take that as an assignment.
Try to research a bit more about it and implement it.
Got it?
So yes, this is pretty much it for this entire notification module and see you next time.