Alright everyone, welcome to one more new chapter.
In this chapter we are basically going to play around polylines and bunch of map settings
that we have already seen in chapter number one, but that is just a surface level knowledge.
Here we are reusing it just to understand and taking much more context out of it.
Got it.
So basically we are again going to implement that inside this mini project.
So, let us move ahead and start implementing it.
First of all, let me take some demo coordinates and I can say demo points of the cities.
So, we have longitude, latitude and longitude for Delhi same with Mumbai and then same for
Bangalore. Perfect. And let's take three different state variables. So the first state variable
that I have is the traffic, then I have a satellite, then I have a selection. All right.
And let me create here one property for polylines as well.
So, this is what we have, this is the ID route coordinates and then a color and then this
is what we basically have.
Right now, this buttons, I do not need it anymore.
So, I can definitely comment them out so that we have better space just to use it.
And let me also create one marker.
Perfect.
So how my marker is basically going to look something like this.
A marker, points we are basically mapping all of them for the specific there coordinates
that we have.
Got it.
And then same title, snippet and direct draggable as false for now.
Then what I will do, I can simply go to my Google Maps, you will see that we already
have this thing, but below this we have something known as properties, yes we know that.
Inside this first thing is traffic enabled, I can say here the traffic.
Nice, same I can have a map type, map type can be type of satellite or this can be basically
if we have a satellite then simply say map dot Google maps dot map type dot basically
I wanted to show here the satellite.
Hopefully this will work.
Otherwise, basically show the standard one, got it?
So if I just copy this and here if I just try to paste that instead of satellite, I
wanted to have the standard, okay, we do not have standard, maybe we can go with normal.
Hopefully this will work, nothing is break, I think yes, nothing is breaking for now.
nice and then in same way we can have a selection enabled is equals to the selection state variable
that we have perfect and below this again but I can have I can have some other buttons
don't need this one.
So again let me import the button.
on press again set camera to this specific coordinate and zoom so this is dilly this
is Mumbai and this is Bangalore alright no problem now let's add a bunch of UI control
one is for we can say traffic toggle another one is for satellite and the another one is
for selection through or false.
So, we already have bunch of toggles just below this I can paste it nice.
So, now you will see we have one traffic the moment I enable this and what if I go little
closer hopefully I can see that ok.
Let me see the in satellite view, let me go little back.
Why I am not be able to see something, maybe because of internet?
Yes, I think my internet is not connected, let me try to reconnect it, cool.
They are checking my quality, nice.
Now let me say this and let me try to reload it once.
Perfect and yes, let us go towards the Delhi hopefully this will take me towards that and
yes now if I simply open this traffic look at that this is how they are basically showing
the traffic of Delhi and the one of the dangerous traffic that we have in Bangalore and look
at that.
This is how the traffic of Bangalore look like.
Yes, look at that.
Cool.
In same way you can view all of them in properly satellite view.
Now it's up to you and this is the magic of Google Maps.
Perfect.
Look at that.
Let's go to Delhi and again you can little make it closer, closer, closer.
This is how they are basically going to show you the specific traffic if we have.
Yes, look at that.
Nice.
So, this is how you can basically use bunch of other properties as well, perfect.
So, hopefully you guys are able to understand them, nice.
So, yep, this is pretty much it for this entire we can say module and see you next time.