Alright everyone and welcome to one more new module in this module we are going to talk
about camera, media and audio.
So with the help of Explore Outer how you can deal with your cameras, DK how you can
work with your media and audio.
So in this chapter our main goal is to talking about camera.
Alright, so this is what we are going to talk about expo camera package, a react component.
Yes, this is work as a component that renders a preview of the device's front or back camera.
Expo camera provide a react component.
Yes, that renders a preview of the device's front or back camera.
The cameras parameters such as zoom, torch and flash mode are adjustable.
Using camera view, you can take photos, yes and record videos that are saved to the app
cache.
The component is also capable of detecting barcodes appearing in the preview.
Just run this example and you can see it.
We'll see that in a while.
Don't worry.
And then you will see that something the usage of it.
So I think this is the right time.
Let's move ahead and start using it.
So for that, now I am on my VS code with the module number eight.
Inside this, quickly move ahead and let me install a new project.
So Banex create expo app at the latest app should we go inside the same module eight
folder.
And then let me wait for installation.
Alright, so now we have installed it successfully, let me simply run run reset project.
So this is going to reset my project and amazing, amazing job.
But before writing any single line of code, let's move ahead and try to understand a
bit more about this.
So, the first thing first like in this whole chapter the only focus is on how you can work
with camera, but why do we even need a camera module?
So, that is the main question.
Like let's say you are creating any social media application, you are creating any QR
codes scanner app and something we can say virtual AR features into your apps that you
can do with the help of expo.
So, something document and photos related things in all of that scenarios you need a
camera integration.
So, that's why this module is very important in itself.
So, first thing first for using this module you need to give permission like you can see
that only one camera.
All right.
So, this is the another thing.
Like they also support in web as well.
I think this is the high time.
Let's move ahead and start using it.
So for using it, you need to install this.
So simply copy from here till here.
All right.
And then I can simply say 1x expo install expo camera.
So this is going to install my expo camera and then simply run 1x expo start.
And after starting it, I can simply press a so by this they are going to open that inside my Android phone.
Perfect. So for using it like let's move ahead and I just wanted you to build again a mini project and that project is very important.
So, for that what I can do inside the app or maybe let us be inside it, but in future
we need it.
So, what I can do?
I can simply again create here a folder name as component and inside this I will simply
going to say here camera component or something
CameraScreen.tsx and RNFES and I can simply say this as CameraScreen.
Alright and we don't need any kind of design for now, I can remove it completely and I
can say this as CameraScreen and if I save it, you will see a CameraScreen at the top
of it.
Nice.
Now, let me close it.
So for using the camera, you will see that they are saying you to install it and then
import camera view, camera type and for asking permission, they are providing us a use camera
permission.
Perfect.
So, first of all, let me install few things.
Let me just coming to here and only install here, bunnix expo install, just coming to
here and search for slider because for zooming in and zoom out, we need this slider.
So just coming to here and copy this.
simply paste that here we are not using npx we are using bunx so this is going to be
bunx expo install react native community slider alright so just we are going to keep building
the project and you are eventually going to learn about camera module so let's import
bunch of things from our expo camera
So, I have imported here camera type, camera view, this is the main component, then flash
mode, perfect and use camera permission.
Along with that you will see we have bunch of other thing as well like available lens
change camera mode, ratio, image size, image type, lot of things.
Perfect, but right now we are good to go with this and then I will import bunch of component
as well.
So below this let me just paste it and let me remove this and let me remove this as well.
So I have imported react use ref and use state along with that I also have an image, style
text, touchable opacity and a view.
And at the last I need a slider.
Alright, so let me import my slider as well.
So this slider is coming from the React Native Community / Slider.
Perfect.
Now, let's move ahead and first thing first I wanted you to initialize a ref and then
I can simply say camera ref is equals to use ref just giving for a reference and on a re-render
we don't want it to remount it that's why we are getting a ref and this is going to
be the type of camera view and initialize this as a null.
Perfect.
Along with this, I also wanted you to initialize bunch of state variable.
Let me explain you about each of them.
First we have a type.
This type is basically for your front camera or your back camera.
If you just hover over it, you will see we have two type of camera type.
First is front camera and second one is back camera.
Then we have same for flash and here you will see off.
So I think let's keep this as an auto and then we have a zoom for zooming it out and
photo you are.
So whenever you click any photo, we wanted to grab that as well.
All right.
So now let's move ahead and first thing we are going to ask for a permission.
So, for that you can simply say const permission and then second thing is going to be as request
permission is equals to use camera permission yes and you will see like we have this use
camera permissions if this permission is given granted.
Or like let me just simply come into here and say if we don't have any permission, then
I simply wanted to say checking permission.
All right, then I will return here a safe area view with the design.
So first of all, let me paste all of my designs for it.
And again, you will find all the design into the same rapport.
So I just wanted you to follow along with me.
So, I am just pasting all the design because I don't want it to waste your and my time
on designing stuffs.
This is not a design class, this is an expo class.
So, main feature is on understanding all the expo features.
I hope so I am making sense.
Perfect.
So, what we have did here, I have just written here permission and request permissions.
If we don't have any permission, we are simply saying here checking the user's permission,
but this permission have one property name as granted.
Look at that.
So, if not of permission is granted, then I will say here camera permission is required
and then we are simply going to say grant permission.
Perfect.
And then for granting permission, we are going to call this function request permission and
then you will ask for allow or deny something like that.
So, first of all, let me just return it.
And we are returning a view which is showing us a text as camera permission is required
and then a touchable opacity which is basically on press triggering this function request
permission and this request permission if I just save it and you will see something
like this perfect and look at that.
Module 8 needs permission for accessing camera.
You have already granted permission to another expo experience allow module 8 to also use
it.
So, I think let me just simply press and allow and yes, now we are able to see this.
Perfect.
Now, inside this return, what I wanted you to do, simply say here, safe area view and
this safe area view is going to have a style as styles.container.
Perfect.
And then first thing, the main component that we have is camera view where you are actually
going to see your camera.
Perfect, so let me just come into here and say here camera view and inside this camera
view I will simply say ref, this ref is going to be camera ref and then style is going to
be as styles.camera and then facing, so facing is going to be as.
type of the camera I wanted to have so I will simply say type perfect they also accept you
something as flash and flash is also going to be flash mode and last thing is we have
a zoom so now if I save it and you will see something like this alright and why I am seeing
not the whole camera, maybe what if I reload it once.
Perfect.
All right.
So I think no problem.
Let's move ahead and first of all design it completely.
Then we'll fix it.
All right.
So right now in same way, we, like you will see that right now we have a view at this
point.
Maybe I need to fix this.
Like if we don't have any permission, we are showing this.
Alright guys, so the main issue is here you will see that right now they are wrapped inside
a view and if I go outside of it now look at that.
This is showing us inside a full screen.
Perfect.
Nice.
And if I just take it out and look at that this is my beast and you will just see my keyboard
my hand.
Alright.
Perfect.
So let me just keep it here.
I just don't want to show you everything.
Right now perfect but yes our camera is open and I hope you guys are able to see that.
Nice.
So this is your main camera view.
But is this enough?
Like I just wanted to zoom it, I wanted to click pictures, I wanted to...
like I just wanted to change it like from back to front, front to back how I can do it.
So for that let's move ahead and start adding camera controls.
So for that we have a view and this view have a style and inside this style so we have a
style.
top controls and inside this we have let's say a touchable opacity.
This is basically used to show we can say lightning like this is for setting flash mode
on or off.
Perfect nice look at that.
In same way, just below this we can have another touchable opacity, but at that time, this
is for changing the camera position.
So you will see the set type either in front or either in back.
And if I save it, and if I just try to show you like right now you will see the camera
side is in.
back perfect but in same way if I just turn it out and I hope so you guys are
seeing me for the first time here so hi to all of you perfect so this is how you
can basically change the side of our camera from a front to back and back to
front alright
Nice, so this is how you can basically control it.
In same way, let's move ahead and let me add a zoom in and zoom out controls as well.
So for that, these are our top controls.
Just the bottom of it, we can have another view and this view can have a style and this
style is going to be a styles.bottom.
Let me just come into it and say bottom controls and then I can show my zoom slider something
like this.
Perfect.
So, I am getting this.
Can't find the name as slider.
Alright, so I need to import slider.
So just give me a minute.
And let me import my slider.
So this is at this point.
Perfect.
Now if I save it.
Oh, what just happened?
This is my slider, alright and if I unable to resolve from component this, alright I
think my slider name will come from here, alright.
So the name is different, it will be imported from here I hope, perfect.
Unable to resolve this, why?
As I have installed it, let me try to reinstall it.
So let me come into here and then 1x expo install this component and let me just fix
my installation command.
invalid project root. Why? I am inside my module. Let me copy this once again. Let me
simply write 1x, expo install, react native component. Alright, we have installed it successfully.
Let me import this from here as well.
Perfect and now if I save it and if I come into here and if I reload it, alright let
me close it, let me try to rerun it maybe right now this will work.
Sometimes this things is pretty normal, no problem.
Perfect, now let me try to reload it and as I said look at that, now you are able to see
that this zoom button and as I just zooming it you will see this is how you can zoom it,
you can go back, you can zoom it once again and you can go back.
Alright, so yes, I hope you are loving this, this is how you can basically control your
entire camera hardware from the expo router, I mean this is the power of expo, nice.
Let's add a capture button, so below this view, I just wanted you to paste this capture
button, this capture button is going to call a take photo.
And, this take photo is basically going to basically save your photo and cache memory
for few seconds.
So, at the bottom of permission granted, I will simply going to say sync function and
this is going to be a stake photo.
And, this take photo is basically if we have camera ref dot current, yes then you can simply
say const photo is equals to await camera ref dot current dot take picture async, yes
this is the function, this is the API provided by expo router.
And you can give here the quality, alright so let me simply say quality as 0.7 and if
we have a photo then I can simply say set photo URI equal to photo dot look at that
base 64, format height but I just wanted to see my photo URI.
Along with this, like how you can see the output of your photo.
So it's pretty easy, like below this capture button and out of this view, we can simply
show a preview model.
So let me just paste it entirely, easy.
Let me copy that UI and paste it.
So you will see, let me first of all import my image from React Native.
whatever if I have any photo URI then and only render this model.
And you will see the image and whatever the photo is coming and in same way you can set
this to null and like this is simple just alert photo saved and let me just save it
and try to rerun this.
All right.
So, let me try to click my photo.
So, if I just simply say cheese.
And if I click it, look at that.
In few seconds you are able to, I don't know the sound is comes to you, come to you or
not, but look at that.
This is the photo which is taken by our camera screen app.
And if I simply press on save, alright you can definitely save this inside your, let
me first of all flip it.
So, definitely you can save this up inside your gallery, inside your document in cache
memory by using expo file.
Now it is up to you how you want it to take it, but this is the power of expo and you
can zoom in, zoom out and I do not know, but for some reason my flashlights are not working
here.
If it is working on your device then let me know, but alright I mean here you will see
can't turn on torch because the light isn't used but I don't know why I am not able to
control it, but it's fine I mean if this is working then everything is definitely going
to work perfectly.
So, this is the end of our this shifter and in this shifter we have talked about how you
can use camera.
Perfect.
So, this is the end of the shifter and see you next time.