Hey everyone and welcome to one more new module.
In this module we are going to learn about navigation with react native apps.
We will start with what is navigation, why we need it and then understand the different
navigation patterns mobile apps use in modern era.
We will also compare React navigation and re-expo router so you know why we are teaching
you both.
Perfect.
Nice.
Now, the first question that is arise is why navigation is important.
Perfect.
Why navigation is important in mobile apps.
So, in mobile apps, we rarely have a single screen.
Make sense or not?
Let's say this is your mobile.
Perfect.
And in mobile screen, let's say you are using WhatsApp and I'm just calling it WP.
Make sense?
No problem.
So, let's say you are using WhatsApp.
So, WhatsApp have multiple screen.
One screen is your normal home screen.
Another screen, let's say these days we have community screen.
And then you also have something known as status screen.
So WhatsApp have multiple screen.
In same way, if you are using Instagram, let me call it IG.
So you again have, let's say a feed or home page.
We can say that in same way.
We also have profile page here.
In the same way, you also have real page here, real page or screen, whatever you wanted to
call it.
So each application into your mobile, they have multiple screens.
So managing and popping between these screens, let's say you wanted to go home screen to
status, then how you can move in react native and export.
Same for now.
We don't have any mechanism for that.
We don't have anything inbuilt for that.
So that's why user always needs to move from A screen to B screen.
Make sense?
Let's say this is A screen and they wanted to move to B or C.
Makes sense, so navigation is not just showing different screen, so this is also concern,
navigation is not just showing different screen, it must feel natural and native.
Let's say if you are using Android then you feel that yes this is how Android applications
are switching between them, they are switching screens between them.
Perfect. Like we have back buttons, we have screen transition.
You users should be able to go forward, go back,
jump any part of the app.
Like they can easily navigate between your multiple screen of the
application. So I hope so I'm making sense. So in short,
Perfect, in short good navigation improves user flow and app usability.
So this is why we need, this is one of the reason we need navigation.
Perfect.
Cool, so for understanding navigation inside react native, we need to understand a core
react navigation library, which is routing and navigation for react native and web apps.
If I just simply press on redox and just give you a quick overview of it, so what follow
within the fundamental section, cool, alright, they are just saying you need this much of
prerequisite all of that.
So, if I just simply go to Hello React Navigation, cool, let's just try to read it and try to
understand, don't worry, you will understand everything, just give me a minute.
In web browser, you can link to different pages using anchor tag, yes we know that,
let's say if you are in a web browser, then what you can do, you can simply have multiple,
let's say if you have about page, if you have, let's say let me just simply write, we have
index.page.
index.html page, we have about.html page.
So if you wanted to move from about to index and index to about, we are using something
known as anchor tag.
No problem.
Yes, when the user click on the link, the URL is push, just keep this in mind, push
to the browser history stack.
Perfect, I'll just tell you what is this.
When the user press the back button, the browser pops the item from top of the history stack.
So active page is now previously visited page.
All right, they are just complicating thing.
They are basically telling you, let's say just listen to me carefully, just track my
cursor.
Now, I am on home page, no problem.
The moment I click on read docs, I am on docs/getstarted.
So now I have history.
What is that history?
If I just simply press on back, I am redirected to the page where I am coming from.
Easy, so this is what they are talking about.
So if I just come into here and in same way React Navigation's native stack navigator,
so like how React native is allowing you to move between screens and maintain a stack,
I hope so you guys know a data structure about stack.
I hope cool so provide a way for your app to transition between screen and manage navigation
history cool.
So let's move ahead and we will see that how you can do so that so for that definitely
you need this much of libraries but now in mobile app you will see a bunch of different
navigation patterns.
If I just simply coming to here and write navigation.
patterns, so what is the navigation patterns that we have?
Like first pattern for navigation is something known as stack navigation.
What is stack navigation?
If I just try to explain you, screens are stack one top of other.
Perfect, let's say this is a screen 1, you have screen 2 in same way.
You have screen 3, screen 4.
So this is how this tagged on top of each other.
Perfect.
You can push a screen and you can let's just say you can pop a screen.
This is like moving forward and backward in browser like something like this.
You are going backward, you are going forward.
This is what they are talking about.
Cool, so basically this is again same way, so let's just say this is your home page,
from home page, home screen you are going towards a detail page, we can say that you
are going towards detail page and from detail page.
Let me just put them up.
And from detail page you are let's say moving to profile page.
So this is how you are basically going to do so this.
Perfect.
Now we have another way and another navigation pattern which is known as tab navigation.
What is tab navigation? Tab navigation something like this. You will see that we have text,
we have code like you can definitely this is not exactly navigation but this that is
how they are going to look to you. Let's suppose this is your mobile app and at the very bottom
and also at the top, they can be anywhere.
Perfect, you have a bar with tab at bottom or top, doesn't matter.
And then from here you can switch between screen without stacking them.
So make sure to keep that in mind, without stacking them you can switch between screen.
Perfect, so let me just simply write switch between screens without stacking them.
Perfect, let's say you have something known as, if I just try to give you an example here,
let me change the color.
Cool.
Let's say this is your home page.
This is your search and this is your profile.
Perfect.
And again, you have here home icon, you have let's just say here something else as well.
I am just demonstrating for you guys.
Let's just say this is your home icon in same way you have another icons as well cool and
when you click on home you are on home page when you click on let's just say detail page
then you are on detail and in same way if you click on profile you are on profile and
again you are not stacking them you are just switching between screen without stacking them
perfect.
Now, let's move ahead and start talking and again I am going to explain you each of them
in their separate chapter.
I am just giving you a bunch of theory about navigation with React navigation.
Perfect.
Cool.
And in same way we have another pattern that is known as drawer navigation.
So how this drawer navigation is going to work?
Drawer navigation means a side menu that slides in.
Perfect.
And when you click on something like if you are using a Google, I mean YouTube, perfect.
Then YouTube always showing you this.
Here you have a bunch of other options as well to show like home, trending, your preferences. Cool.
And this is basically good for large app with many sections. Perfect.
This is good for a large apps with many sections that you have.
And then another one that we have is known as model screens.
What is this model screen?
Model screens means let me just simply write what this model screens means.
Let's say this is your main screen and on over this current screen, yes on over this
current screen you are going to see another screen.
Perfect.
So this is what your model screens means.
This is basically commonly used for if I just try to write common for alerts or something
which is in temporary action we can say that.
So this is what we are basically going to use.
So again if I just try to explain you like how many navigation pattern that we have,
I just simply write navigation patterns.
So, the first pattern that we have is named as snack navigation.
Perfect.
The another navigation pattern that we have is named as, let me just try to put them.
I don't know.
Yes.
So, then another one that we have is the tab navigation.
Perfect.
So, let me simply write tab navigation and the third one that we have is known as drawer
navigation.
This is very rarely used, but still and then in same way, we also have.
model screens models you are going to use a lot perfect.
So this is your another one and in same way we have the third one and in same way we have
another one as well.
So let me just simply write them here as well cool.
So these are all the navigation patterns that we have.
No problem.
This is just a theory chapter.
Now let's move ahead and try to understand we have two type of navigations like two type
of libraries we can use.
But right now we are understanding react navigation.
And then another one is expo router and this is what expo router we are going to use in
all our upcoming chapters.
Why we are understanding and why we are learning about react navigation because this is the
base.
Perfect.
I can simply write here react navigation versus expo router.
All right, let me just simply coming to here and write something like this.
So what is React Navigation and Xporouter?
So now there are different ways to implement navigation and these are the two popular ones
in React native ecosystem.
Like React Native is what?
React Native is a component based library.
Perfect.
Make sure to keep that in mind.
This is component based library.
But when it's come to expo router, this is built on top of React Native and this is file
based routing system.
Like if you have ever used Next.js, they are resembling with them very much.
So this is going to be file-based routing system.
Perfect.
Here in React navigation, you will see that from upcoming lectures, you will explicitly
define stacks, tab, drawer, screen options, headers, a lot of other things.
And they work with expo and non-expo apps as well.
And this is very powerful and flexible.
And this is definitely they have large community and their ecosystem are very, very, very good.
You can definitely go with it and you have much more control over it.
But when it's come to expo router, they are using file based routing.
You can organize screen inside a folder like what I mean by inside a folder.
Let's say you have an app folder and inside this you can create app/home, app/about, app/details.
They all are treated as a route segment.
Perfect, and they automatically create from files.
Expo router is integrated, yes, they are integrated with Expo if you are using it and definitely
we are learning Expo one of the best thing that you can learn in today's era, form while
development and this is ideal for quick setup and file centering structure.
Perfect.
So, I hope so I'm making sense like React navigation is component based and this expo
router is also built on top of React navigation itself.
But now let's move ahead and one question arise.
Why do we even need to learn about React navigation when we are already learning about expo and
in future we're definitely going to learn about expo routers.
But this is the extra chapter and this is the optional chapter again if you don't want
it to cover it, it's completely optional you can skip it.
But I just wanted to suggest you to watch it and build up a mini project that we are
going to build which is Pokemon Go, not Pokemon Go app but we are going to use here multiple
screens and implement a very nice Pokemon app.
Perfect, so why do we even need to learn about React Navigation?
So again even though we will transition to Expo router later but understanding React
Navigation is important because it teaches you the core navigation concepts.
Perfect, you need to understand about core navigation concept like in same way whenever
you wanted to learn about react native, you need to understand about reacts in same way
when you wanted to learn about X-For router, you need to have you need have you basically
need to have a basic understanding of.
React navigation perfect like many third party libraries still assume that you are using
navigations kind of expo router also mirror many react navigation patterns under the hood.
So expo router also using it.
And you will know what happened behind the file based routing.
So always you are going to understand like what is happening behind the scene.
Perfect behind the file based routing in Expo.
So I hope so now you have a clear path.
Why we basically need to learn about react navigation first.
Cool.
So yeah, this is just a basic theory about a react navigation and why do we even need
navigation from next chapter we are going to install this and start understanding bunch
of concept about it.
So yeah, this is pretty much it and see you next time.