Alright everyone and welcome to one more new module.
From this module we are going to talk about data storage and file systems in expo.
So what is this?
So basically whenever you wanted to store some sort of data locally, so for webs we
already have session storage, local storage.
But when it's come to mobile app, what is the solution for it?
So we have three different solutions and each of them have different use cases like first
one is async storage.
This is a separate initially they natively support into react native or we can say expo,
but for now they maintained separately.
We'll talk about it.
Don't worry.
Then we have this Expo Secure Store.
Then we have this Expo SQLite and then Expo file system.
This is basically more of a file system related thing.
So this is the chapter number one and in this chapter we are basically going to talk about
async storage.
So now let's move ahead and start talking about async storage and what is this?
So basically, we can say whenever you wanted to let your app save data locally on a device
like many mobile apps need to remember things we can say that and definitely.
So in terms of user preferences, some settings or some other information.
Even after the user close the app and we can say refresh it and reopen it, we want it to
sync up and pop up all the previously stored data kind of that.
So this is where a sync storage came in the picture.
So, async storage is a key value storage system.
Yes, async storage is basically store data into key value format.
Like they store data asynchronously.
This means they are not going to block any UI for you.
You can smoothly use your app and in background they are going to store your data.
Now, the second thing is and like second thing is this is async.
Third, we can say they persist your data and that is why we basically need it.
And then this is unencrypted.
Yep.
Like we can say that whenever you wanted to store a non-sensitive data, so it is good for
storing.
Non-sensitive data. Cool.
This is basically good for storing non-sensitive data.
Like as I told you earlier, like user preferences, some app state,
but not secure for sensitive data.
We can say like storing passwords.
Storing tokens, storing AI API keys, these are not a good practice to follow with async
storage.
For that we have this Expo secure store.
We'll come to it in next chapter.
Cool.
So now let's move ahead and we'll see basically how you can use it and how you can implement
it.
So for that we have this website.
Perfect, name as react native async storage where you will basically find it.
So you just simply need to go to the documentation and search for async storage and after searching
you will found this doc page.
And here you will see that async storage is our synchronous, unencrypted, persistent key
value storage for react native apps.
And we can say for expo they both are same.
It has a simple API and it is good choice for storing small amount of data.
It is good.
It is also good choice for storing data that does not need encryption.
such as user preferences or we can say app store.
So understanding more about it, you can simply press on async storage documentation and you
will be redirected to this page.
And after that, you can basically click here to go to latest version because we wanted
to go latest.
And then this is the command you are going to run for implementing it.
I think.
Let's go to the previous one.
Yes.
And simply press on see installation and go with it.
Cool.
Yes.
And let me copy this command only this.
And I have already installed a basic expo app and I have resetted it and open into my
Expo Go app.
Perfect.
So I hope so.
These things you guys can do by yourself.
And now let me just simply open my terminal and inside my terminal I can simply run burnx
Expo install at the rate react native async storage.
slash async storage and then simply hit this.
So after hitting it you will just wait for few seconds and you will just let me just
write back and alright now you can see that in fraction of seconds in less than 7 seconds
We have installed it successfully.
Now how you can use it?
So for using it you can simply press on usage and this is how you can store it.
So the first step is always going to be import this and then use it.
So, let's move ahead and we will see that how we can use it.
So for that let me go inside the index.tsx files.
Alright.
And here, so the first thing I wanted to do is to import this.
So for importing it, I can simply say async storage.
Prom, add the rate, react native, async storage, async storage.
All right.
And let me off my AI.
I think we are already done with it.
Cool.
Now for stimulating it, I just wanted you to do a bunch of settings with me.
Yes, you have to do it.
Like first thing is you can simply maintain a state variable simply say output and then
this is going to be set output and this is equals to use state.
Perfect.
And I will just keep this as empty.
And then I am going to create here.
a simple utility just to simulate a lot of things for you.
I will call it a log and this log is going to accept a message and then this is going
to show us the output.
Easy.
And whatever the output is here like previous one, I am basically going to show that.
like backslash and just to show them in a show the string into new line and whatever
the message will come cool and this will going to be type of any because this can be of string
this can be of an object so let's keep this as an array as in any.
Perfect.
So the first thing that I wanted to understand is how you can store the data.
So for storing the data, you can already see this is the simple method.
And what is that method?
Method is a sync storage dot set item.
And, then you need to give the key for it and the value.
Simple, straightforward, nothing rocket science, perfect.
Alright, so let's move ahead and I am going to say this as cons example 1.
And then I am going to create here a sync method.
First thing before using it, I always wanted to clear all the previous logs that we have.
So let me just simply, you need not to do so all of this.
You can just directly run it and see the output, but I wanted to simulate a lot of other methods
as well.
That's why I'm doing this much of thing.
Perfect, so let me simply say set output as an empty string, not rocket science at all.
Perfect, so here before calling anything I just wanted to clear out everything.
Perfect, and then I can simply say await async storage.
Alright, where is my async storage?
I think they just get out of it.
No problem, let me re-import it.
And let me try to reuse it.
So asyncstorage.setitem and then first thing is always going to be the key.
So let me say this as username and then second thing is always going to be value.
Let me simply say name as Suraj.
Easy.
And then let me just create a log and I can say saved.
Perfect, saved word, username is equal to solage.
No problem.
Simple, easy thing.
Perfect.
And now what you can do, you can simply come into here and then let me try to design it
a bit.
Perfect.
So just give me a minute.
Let me say just for right now, I am basically going to use here the pressable.
All right.
And then this pressable is basically going to save me a text.
Text is going to be save item into storage.
No problem.
Perfect.
And let me rerun my application.
Burn X, expose start.
Perfect.
And then let me reload it.
Cool.
So you can definitely reference this chapter specifically just for this async storage in
future as well.
And I can say on press is basically going to be as example one.
Perfect.
So the moment I simply say save item and then if I check my logs nothing happened.
Why?
Let me reload it.
Cool.
What if I say alert instead of log?
What if I say alert?
Cool.
Perfect.
And then if I once again click over this saved and you will see saved user name is equals
to source.
This means data is saving.
Now, how I can see the output?
So for seeing the output what I can do I mean this is not necessary to do so but let's do
it.
Let me below this let me add here a view perfect this view is going to show the title as output
and then a scroll view of showing the output like this output basically.
like this one. Cool. And let me just simply apply the design for it. So, let me bring
that cool and I will say this as const styles is equals to style.
style sheet dot create.
Perfect.
And then inside this, I am basically going to paste it.
Now let me see what happened.
Where is my style sheet?
Maybe this is not. Let me import my scroll view.
Let me go back one more back.
Style sheet and this will come from react native and this will create and then I am
going to paste this design.
Cool.
So, now you will see that we have the design.
Sorry, let me fix it.
Cool.
Now we are good to go.
Perfect.
And let me import my scroll view once again.
And now if I go to here, you will see this something like, so let me fix this by saying
here and this is going to be the styles.container.
Let me create here one container for it.
So this is going to be as container and this container is going to have a flex of one and
All right.
This is going to be the padding of 20.
And now if I save it, you will see that we have this output.
And now instead of alert, if I simply say this as log and if I say save item, you will
see saved this and this is how we can basically simulating it.
Cool.
So now we have already seen how you can save the data.
Perfect.
Now let's move ahead and then I wanted to see basically how you can get the data.
So for getting the data, let me simply create here example 2 and this is going to be as
simple as sync.
And for before getting it, I wanted to clear everything that I have and then simple await
and before awaiting it, I wanted to get it.
So I can simply say there very easily, I can say const value and this value is basically
equal to await and very, this is very straightforward as equal to we can say local storage.
So, asyncstorage.getitems, go get item not items and then you simply need to pass the
key.
So, the key is user username and then I can simply use my log and then I can show whatever
the value is coming.
Perfect and in same way I can copy this.
Perfect.
I can paste this.
I can use here example2 and then I can say
Get items.
Perfect.
And now if I press on get items, you will see this is the data which is coming from
localhost.
Let's say instead of Suraj, I have changed this to Karan.
Perfect.
And if I press simply as save item into storage, then we definitely, I can change this as well.
And if I simply say you can see that this is the data and if I press get item you will
see this is the data which is coming from a sync storage.
So this is how you can set items, this is how you can get item in same way let me tell
you in same way you can definitely store data into JSON format as well.
You can store like if you just simply press on API, you will see we have a lot of methods.
I don't want it to get all of, I just don't want it to cover all of them.
You will definitely figure out like very straightforward, very simple.
Perfect.
Let me just try to show you the remove item.
How you can basically remove all the items that are present inside your local system.
So very easy.
I can simply say example 3 and I will rename this to example 3.
Perfect and what I can do?
I can simply going to use here the remove item function.
Perfect and after that.
Things is going to be very easy.
So instead of this, I can simply say this as remove item.
Now how this remove item work?
Nothing.
You just simply need to call it.
So we need not to do anything else.
I can simply say data removed.
Easy.
And then in same way I can copy this, I can paste this, this is very easy.
This is example 3 and then I can say delete items.
Let me save it.
Let me press on delete item, you will see data removed.
And now if I press on get item, you will see I am getting null.
Why I am getting null?
Because every data that is inside my async storage.
has wiped out. Cool. I can again save the data. I can again get the data, but if I delete
it then I am going to get nothing. Cool. In same way you can check for multi get, multi
set, multi merge. This means you can merge more than one data.
Now, we also have a clear basically means this is going to remove all the items that
are present inside your async storage.
So I mean this is also easy.
Now we have use async storage hook.
So, hook like interface that we are experimenting with.
Now they are basically experimenting this.
So this will change in nearest future to fully leverage Hooks API.
So I mean this is again an optional thing.
They are basically providing you a bunch of method out of the box.
So, instead of just importing this, listen to me, instead of importing this and then
extract this from here and then use it, they are providing you a basic simple hook and
inside this hook you have get item, you have set item, you can merge item, you have remove
item.
And this is how you can extract them and use them.
So I think this is pretty much it for this chapter because there is nothing as such groundbreaking
into it.
This is a bunch of simple APIs and you just need to know how you can use it.
So, I am assuming that this is very easy for you guys to understand what is happening.
This is just my assignment and take this as an assignment.
Try to create all the examples and use it and see that inside the output.
Cool.
Design it as much as you want.
And, yep, now it's up to you.
So this is pretty much it for the chapter number one where we have learned about async
storage.
In our next chapter, we are going to talk about bunch of other features like secure
So yeah, this is pretty much it and see you next time.