Alright everyone, welcome to chapter number 2 of our map. In chapter number 1, we have
basically seen all of the features which is provided by expo map. But right now, our main
focus is to understand them one by one once again so that we have a proper command on
to the expo map.
So, the first thing again, let's move ahead and try to understand more about camera positioning.
Perfect.
So, with the help of a mini project, we are going to understand more about camera positioning.
I already have my build ready as you guys can see.
This is the previous application we have built.
This is very weird and very bad app.
But definitely, we are just seeing the overview of ExpoMap, what you can do with that.
But in this let's move hand and try to create a mini project.
So what is the idea of the mini project is we simply wanted to have a screen.
Let's say this is a screen, onto this screen we have map and inside this map we basically
have a button that move the camera to different cities.
All right.
move the camera to different cities.
using longitude and latitude and zone. Perfect. So, what is the key concept for it?
You can see that. Expomap, expose native map view with camera position prop. Yes,
we know that very well. If I just go to my index,
You can see that we have a camera position prop at this point, yes you can see that
we have this camera position prop, yes.
So they basically expose the native map view, nice.
So first that we have is the coordinates and second thing that we have into it is the zoom,
nice.
So, now let us move ahead and definitely we do not need it.
what I will do basically I will.
Create here nodes.md and inside the nodes I will cut this out and I will paste it out
cool.
So, that you have the access of this nodes RNFES and let me say this as index perfect.
So, right now you can see this is how they look to us.
So, first thing is let me import all of the important things that I need.
I need a use state, then I need a button, definitely I don't need this, I'll remove
it in a while and I have imported ashric as map from expo map.
First thing I wanted you to create here a state variable.
So, this state variable showing us some coordinates, first one is the latitude and second thing
is the longitude and then a zoom value, nice.
And then first of all let me copy my design, this is the design, let me paste it and then
what I will do first of all, I will have here axis of view.
This view is first of all going to have a style.
This style is definitely going to be as a map container.
Let me off my AI.
All right.
And what I can do if the platform specific UI, so if the platform OS is iOS, then show
the Apple map.
Otherwise, show the Google map, perfect.
And if I save it, look at that.
This is how the Google map is basically showing to us, nice.
And in same way, we can have a button.
And that button is basically going to show us Delhi, Mumbai, Bangalore and all of them
have their some longitude and latitude positions.
So, inside this view, what I can do?
I can have here a style.
Inside this style, we can have a styles.buttons and inside this styles.buttons, first thing
I can have a button.
Nice.
So, let me import the button from React Native.
This button is basically showing us this deli title.
And then on press they are basically changing the coordinates according to the position.
Easy nothing rocket science.
In same way I can have for Mumbai and in same way I can have for Bangalore.
Let me save it.
So the moment I save it, this is how they are going to look.
Now let us see the moment I press on Mumbai.
I am hopefully redirected to the Mumbai's location.
Nothing is bragged.
Maybe we are too late.
Yes, look at that, exactly we are at somewhere around this varodra and something if I again
press on Bangalore and maybe zoom should be 5, I do not know, but if I put the zoom as
5 and now if I save it and again press on Bangalore, ok.
So, let me change the value of zoom to 9.
Let me again press on Bangalore.
So somewhere definitely we are somewhere here at this location of Bangalore.
Nice.
If I again press on Delhi, New Delhi, Mumbai somewhere to the Mumbai.
Let me go to go with 9 with Mumbai.
Again press somewhere here.
If I again press on Bangalore.
So we are successfully changing the positions.
All right.
So this is how you can basically use this camera position props.
Making sense?
Alright, so what you will basically learn like what is camera position and how coordinates
map to the real world places and how zoom controls all of these things.
Perfect.
Nice.
So, yes, we can say this is pretty much it with the camera position prop and see you
next time.