Alright everyone and welcome to one more new lecture and today we are going to deep dive
into something really exciting and that is known as network API.
Perfect, so this is the main thing that we are going to learn definitely this is the
chapter number one of our complete module on device and system APIs.
And by the end of this lecture, you will know how to check internet connectivity and handle
network changes into your expo or react native apps.
So with that, grab your coffee, open your code editor and let's get started.
Perfect.
So the first thing is, what do you understand by network API?
What is network API?
So, the network API inside the expo allow us to check if the device is connected to
internet or not.
Perfect.
First thing is, is device is connected to internet or not.
This is the first thing.
Second, you can know your connection type.
Got it, you can know your connection type, but we can say we can say that is, is it a
Wi-Fi, is it a cellular data and is it something else?
Got it.
And we can even check for network changes in real time.
Got it, we can check for network changes in real time and get the device IP address, MAC
address, whatever you wanted to get.
Alright, so this is why we basically need a network API and this is the network API is
basically allow you to do.
Perfect.
No, the biggest question is arise.
Why do we even need the network API?
So let's try to imagine a scenario.
Alright, let's say you are creating a video player application.
Alright, this is your video player application and you wanted to create this, but you only
wanted to auto play on Wi-Fi.
So basically what I'm talking about only auto play videos on Wi-Fi auto play videos on Wi-Fi
and what we can say that.
This is the first requirement.
Second, show warning on cellular data.
Let's say you are creating a video streaming application and a video app.
You wanted to show the warning whenever user on the cellular data because video streaming
take a lot much of data.
Got it?
Lot of data.
And third, pause download when you are offline.
Got it.
These are bunch of features you wanted to implement.
So pause downloads when we are offline.
So how you can do so this?
So that's why you need a network API.
Let's say another example.
You are creating a shopping cart.
All right.
And we can say a shopping app.
So that shopping app.
is first to fall prevent the checkout, yes they are going to basically prevent the checkout
and let me just give my stop, alright.
So they are basically going to prevent the checkout whenever a user cellular or basically
we can say whenever user is
offline. This is the first use case. Second use case is you wanted to show no internet
banner. You wanted to cache data for offline viewing. In all of that case, you need a,
we can say network API. Third, you are creating a chat application whenever you wanted to,
let's say you are just chatting with your friend and let me just try to grab your friend.
Let's say this is your friend got it?
This is your user.
Let me grab here.
Perfect.
You are chatting with someone.
All right.
And this is you and you are chatting with this guy.
But in between you get offline.
So in that case, whatever message you have sent, we are going to store that message.
We can say inside a queue.
Basically a place where whenever I am online
I am again going to get all of the message and start sending them.
Alright, start sending them.
This is how we can say that.
So without this API, your app would not know it's offline until it crashed.
Got it?
That's why we need this network API.
Perfect, like how it's actually work if I just try to explain you it visually how it's
actually work.
Let's say this is your, we can say your expo app.
All right, this is your expo app.
No problem.
Perfect.
And first thing that we have is the expo app is have network API.
We know that expo app have a network API.
So this network API is first of all going to check your connectivity.
Like it is basically going to check your connection is you are connected or not.
Then this is basically going to check your network type like how you can check network
type, is it a Wi-Fi, is it a cellular, is it something else?
So then this third thing is what we can do, we can basically check like what is the network
type for it.
And then at the end, there is always an event listener for it, like they always keep listening
to the alright and then at the end what you will do, you have basically access of the
device network.
So, with the help of this network API at the end, we have the access of we can say the
device.
network API, this is your device and then we have access of all the network APIs which
is available to us, perfect.
I can say simply device network, perfect.
So now let's move ahead and start using it.
So for that what you can do, you can first of all simply copy this installation command,
we know that.
and then let me open my terminal and simply run "bunx create expo app"
wanted to create in module 9 folder
let me hit this and let's just wait for application installation
alright guys so now we have installed it successfully
you can see that how much time it took, it's fine sometime it take it
and after that let me move ahead and reset it so "bun run reset"
So, this is going to reset my project, simply say no, clear it, bun x expo start.
So, this is going to start my application, let just wait for it and let us clear it,
we do not need it anymore and then I can simply press on A, then this is going to start my
application, what just happened, something went wrong.
Okay, if I try to reload it, nothing just happened.
Cool.
What if if I try to scan this, maybe this will work right now.
So just give me a minute.
Let me scan this.
Let me open it here.
Hopefully this will work right now.
Sorry about that.
You can go back to expo home and try to reload this.
All right.
So let me try to restart it as bunnix expo start.
Alright, hopefully this will work right now.
We have installed everything correctly.
Then why this is not working?
Cool.
Maybe that is my network issue.
And if I again press on a skipping expo go version validation in offline mode.
Alright, so I'm getting in offline mode.
That is the issue.
Actually, I am connected to my internet.
Yes.
I am connected to this internet then why this is not working.
Alright, so actually I have reconnected my physical device and I think right now this
is going to work fine, cool because I am getting this bundling option.
So this means this is going to work.
So let's just wait for this bundling and I think this is finished now, cool.
Alright guys so I have basically reconnected my physical device once again and now this
is working fine alright.
It's fine now you can see that this is how and if I just try to simply say here hello
world and save it.
So, you will see this is how they working nice.
So, now everything is fine, cool.
What next?
Now, let us move ahead and first of all simply visit to this expo network documentation.
You can simply visit and search for expo network.
And then you are redirected to this documentation.
So provide a useful information about the device network such as IP address, Mac, Internet
S, Mac address and airplane mode status.
So simply first of all copy this command and after copying this open a new terminal and
then hit 1x expose install expose network.
So, this is basically going to install this dependency, alright, alright, so in less than
six seconds we have successfully installed it, perfect.
Now what I wanted you to first of all let's move ahead and try to do some basic network
checks like how you can basically do a basic network checks, perfect.
So for that what I wanted you to do is to simply
move ahead and what if I just simply create a component and show that so that we can see
multiple examples, I think yes that is the right approach.
So let me just simply not commence, this is going to be components.
Inside the component first thing I can simply going to say this as basic.
network check dot TSX all right and then RNFES no problem basic network check all right.
Let me save it, let me copy this.
And let me also import that here, perfect basic network check and if I save it, this
is what I am getting, no problem.
Now first of all let's move ahead and simply say import H-trick and first of all let me
off my AI.
Then I can simply import a string as network from expo network.
Nice.
And then what next?
Next let's see that I basically just wanted to check my network state as I'm connected
or as I'm not connected to internet.
Simple.
Let's see how we can do that.
So, for that first thing, what I can do, let me just maintain some state variable, I can
simply say is connected and then set is connected is equals to use state and then initially
I can keep it as null.
Perfect.
And then what I can do, I can simply say network and then set network type.
type and we can say simply again a simple yo state.
Alright and I hope you guys are loving my theme.
Perfect.
So which theme I am using if you are interested into that.
So the theme that I am using right now is whisper vibrant.
Alright this is also good but I don't know for some reason I am not loving it.
Instead I am loving this.
even more.
Alright, now let's move ahead and just create a simple utility and that utility is simply
going to check a network for us.
So check network is equals to async.
And then inside this first thing what I will do I can simply say network state is equals
to await and then let me just get network and for getting the network state if you go
to the documentation you will find something known as network state.
Get network state async, alright, yes, this is the simple function that we are going to
use.
So, I can simply going to call this easy and if I just try to read it, so get the devices
current network state on web navigator.connection.type is not available on browser, alright, we are
also not focusing much on browser.
So, if there is any active network connection.
return state unknown, alright, you can ignore it.
Let's see that how we can get it.
So for now, but I can say if I am connected, so what I will do, I am going to change my
state variable easy, so I can simply say network state dot is connected, easy, I hope
so.
Now they are throwing me an error, what they say argument of Boolean undefined is not assignable
to type of null.
So, what I can do instead I can keep this as right now let me make it as any perfect
for now we can definitely fix it and then let us move ahead and what I will do I can
first of all get my network type or how I can get it I can simply say.
network type, yes network type dot type.
So where is that at this point cool.
So network state not network type sorry my mistake so network state dot type yes look
at that.
Cool and for now I can also keep here any because I don't want it to grab bunch of
states and then show you all right it's fine let's focus here first of all and then what
we can do let's just console that as well easy so I can simply console it.
network state whatever is going to be now.
How I can call it on reload, simply use use effect.
So what if I just simply call here my use effect and inside this use effect I am going
to call this check network method.
Alright, so for logic part we are done.
This is just a basic network check.
So, let me just grab my designs, alright, again you can get all the designs, all the
code file whatever I am writing on to my GitHub, don't worry about that, but for now
let's focus here, cool.
Let me copy my entire design and then try to show you what is they are going to look
to us.
So, let me import button from React Native.
So, I have BC look at that.
They are showing me connected to Wi-Fi and what if I just try to off my Wi-Fi.
Alright and now if I refresh it look at that in real time look at that in real time the
the moment I press on refresh my network status.
Yes, my network status is coming as disconnected.
That's the beauty of network API.
Let me just reconnect it.
Cool.
So just give me a minute.
And yes, just just give me a minute.
Let me reload my application as well and look at that in real time.
We are saying is connected true is internet reachable true and type is again to the Wi-Fi
and let me just reload it once.
Every changes will reflect in a while cool and you will see that right now look at that
now this is connected to it but I think I need to reconnect my application because after
disconnected Wi-Fi my systems
IP address because we are using same Wi-Fi.
So that's why they just mismatch.
So just give me a minute.
Let me try to reconnect my application and I think, alright, I'm still getting no connected
app.
So just give me a minute.
Let me fix it.
Alright.
So now you can see.
We are connected successfully.
Perfect.
Let's move ahead and try to take more examples.
So for that, what we can do, we can create an example to as real-time network listener.
So whenever you change your network state, then we are going to show here online, otherwise
offline, something like that.
Cool.
So, let me go to my components and let me simply say this as why I am making so much
spelling mistake for network, network listener, LISTE and a listener dot TSX, R and FES and
then this is going to be network.
Listener.
All right.
And let me save it.
Let me go to my app and index dot t s x and below this let me try to paste that as well.
Perfect.
So and let me just comment this out cool so that we can have a network listener here.
And again same thing, let me first of all import all of that that I need.
So let me go to my this application and import all of this from here.
Cool.
Let me paste it.
And then.
Nice, and then let's maintain here two state variable, one is status and another one is
a set status.
This is equal to again, use that and initially we can keep the status as checking whatever
you want, I mean it's up to you, cool.
just a simple I can say connection type and then set
connection type and this is again equal to use state, perfect.
And then what we can do in same way, now we are going to basically use here a very nice
utility.
If I take you at the very bottom.
And what if I try to show you, I think this one, add network state listener, cool.
So let us move ahead and start using that, cool.
So very easy to use, let me just simply coming to here and simply go inside a use effect.
Add a dependency and dependency is empty for now.
Inside this what I can do?
I can again say const of subscription is equals to network.addnetworkStateListener and then
they have access of state.
Then a simple callback and let's console everything so that we can have a proper debug
logs.
So network changed.
All right.
First of all, we are tracking for the network change that we have that easy.
And then what I will say if I simply I am going to say state dot if it is to look at
that, now we have three things first is connected is internet reachable true or false simple
and what is the type.
So, if I say state dot is connected then.
I am simply going to say what status as online, no problem, I am simply going to say set status
as online, otherwise set status as offline, perfect and let me format this out, cool.
And what we will do now, I can simply.
it, perfect.
So, but for calling it before that let me just simply say return and whatever we are
subscribed to just simply say subscription.remove so that we have proper demounting as well unmounting
sorry.
Now, let us move ahead and create a simple initial state like initially whenever this
use effect is run we are on which state.
So, for that I can simply create a function name as check initial state and this is equals
to the async and this async is first of all we need to get the state for it.
So, now what we are going to basically say simply say here.
Network, yes, network dot get network status sync simple method, no problem that we did
here perfect and same thing if with the status is connected then simply says connected otherwise
we are going to create here a utility as get name type name.
So how that is?
So, this is basically going to accept a type, alright, for now let me make this as type
of any, perfect.
So, if type is 0, this means none, we are just basically mapping it, perfect, this is
how we are basically mapping it out.
And just simply copy this and initially like this is just for state change, but initially
whenever I run this use effect, then I wanted to show this.
So let me just move ahead and grab my UI for it.
Perfect, and where is that at this point, cool.
So now I have all my UI and let me copy the view for it, perfect, let me save it.
So now you will see if I save it, look at that.
Right now what I am getting?
I am getting the online status.
Perfect.
But what I am saying try turning on and off Wi-Fi or airplane mode.
Let's first basically there is no SIM connected.
But let me just try to go to airplane mode and look at that.
Right now they are showing me a offline.
All right.
But if I just move still I'm offline because I'm not connected to any internet.
Alright, now let me try to basically connect to internet.
Cool.
So just give me a minute, let me reconnect it.
And you can also check the logs in real time.
This is the network state is connected through and is internet reachable.
Let me try to reload it once so that we can see the updated UI.
And yes.
Look at that.
The moment I reloaded it, we are again online.
So this is how you can basically listen to a network state change.
Perfect.
So what is right now happening?
Automatically detects network changes.
and updates UI in real time and we can even say that there is no manual refresh needed
and you can see that proper alive status indicator.
Perfect.
In same way, if you wanted to see.
a bunch of information about your network.
So let me just copy and paste that directly because I just don't want it to stretch that
too much.
So that's why let me just simply copy it and say this as network, network details dot
TSX.
network details, alright. So, first thing let me import all of that what I need easy
no problem till now. So, just give me a minute let me copy this and let me paste it easy
no problem. Now let us maintain a state variable.
This state variable is an object.
So this is network info and we have a empty state.
Is connected initially false?
Is internet reachable null?
What is your IP address?
And then loading true.
Perfect.
And in same way, let me try to create the function that is going to basically fetch me
the IP address.
So this is how we will get it.
First is get network state, we know that.
Then we have initialized here one IP address and if we are connected, then we are basically
getting the networks IP address by using this method.
All right.
And setting the state, no problem till now, easy.
And then for now, let me again mark this as any, so that this is stop crying, perfect.
And we can also show here, if the network info is in loading state, yes.
So, we wanted to show here a simple live indicator.
And whenever for the first time, I coming to here.
I basically wanted to fetch this easy.
So let's see that onto the UI.
UI is bit bigger here but it's fine.
Let me copy that and let me paste it and same with the design.
Let me copy my entire design and paste it.
Alright, now let's close this, let's close this as well and simply go inside index.tsx
we don't need it anymore, simply we need a network details component and now if I save
it, look at that.
We are connected, internet is reachable and this is how I am basically fetching my IP address.
Perfect.
So it's connected, check device connection and is internet reachable, check your actual
internet connections.
So this is how you can basically make decisions on the basis of networks, APIs.
Perfect.
Is it making sense right now?
Like this is all we have discussed till now.
Perfect.
So, this is the end of chapter number one with the help we have basically studied here
how you can use the network API and again there is lot of types, lot of variables as
well.
So, if you just simply go to this documentation and search for types.
So, you will see network state have bunch of types.
Like is connected is internet reachable network state event have Bluetooth, cellular, ethernet,
non other unknown VPN, Wi-Fi, Wi-Max all of this is just your network state types and
this is just a enums.
Perfect along with that we also have some error codes so you can also use it.
So, yes, this is pretty much it for this and now if I just try to give you a simple conclusion,
we have learned what is network API and why we need it, how to check a basic connectivity,
how to listen to our network changes and how to get IP address and detail information and
we have also seen.
A bunch of examples on the real world use cases.
So this is the end of this chapter and see you next time.