Hey everyone and welcome to chapter number one of module two, name as core components
and styling.
In this lecture we are understand, we will understand an important concept in React Native,
name is native component versus core component.
What are native components?
one of the question is arising.
So native components are the actual UI element.
Listen to me carefully.
This is going to be your actual UI elements provided by the OS.
Perfect.
OS means iOS or Android here.
So, native components are the actually UI elements provided by the operating system.
So, let us say if I just try to give you an example and for Apple perfect not Apple, but
just understand this as an iOS.
So, for iOS and then we have Android perfect and then for Android.
So for iOS...
We have like you need not to understand anything for now just listen to me keep your brain
open and just downloading all the things that I am saying to you.
Now we are understanding native components.
Native means actually UI elements provided by the OS you are developing on be it iOS
or Android.
So, in future like whenever you are going to use Objective-C, Shift-UI, then they provide
you their native component like UI view, UI label and then UI button.
In same way on Android they provide you something like this.
They provide you the view, the text view, the button.
Perfect.
So what are they are?
But basically what is view?
What is text view?
What is button?
So, these components, yes, these are all the components and these components are written
in native languages.
So, they are written in native language like we have a lot of native language.
One is SIFT, then we have Objective C, then we have Java and then we have, let's say,
Kotlin.
So, these are the native languages like sift, Objective-C, Java or Kotlin and they are exist
only yes they are exist only inside the native Android or iOS layer perfect they only exist
inside the native iOS or Android layer.
Perfect, they are not directly used in react native and JavaScript code.
So listen to me carefully, they are not directly used in react native and JavaScript code.
So, like you are a react native developer.
So as a react native developer, we do not import or write native components directly.
Perfect.
You never going to write these components directly.
So this is where the core component come.
So what is core component?
If I just simply write what is core components in react native.
So, core components are the components provided by the react native.
Perfect.
These are the component which is provided by the react native that we use inside our
code.
Perfect.
We are going to use this inside our actual code that we are going to write.
Some like if I just try to give you some common core components name.
We have view, we have text, we have image, we have scroll view, we have pressable, lot
of things.
I mean, I can write bunch of here.
So these components are written.
Yes, these components are written inside.
the JS.
And like if I just try to these components are written in JS and act as a cross platform
interface like you can use this view for iOS, you can use this view for Android as well.
So this is the beauty of react native.
So, you write one component and react native internally handles the platform specific implementations
for you.
So, I hope so that make sense.
Perfect.
So, let's say if you are writing any one of them, but if you are writing for iOS.
Let's say you are only writing for let's say you are writing inside the expo or react native
they both are same for now.
So internally they are using react native we knows that expo is using react native internally.
So react native is going to do something they are going to compile that in a way they are
supported inside the iOS.
And same way they are supported inside the
Android as well.
So everything is properly compatible.
Perfect.
So if I just simply try to map that out, so this is how they are going to work.
We have view text image.
We have written everything inside the expo.
Expo is using react native internally.
React native is going to do the implementation, which is a platform specific implementation
like iOS for Android.
So, this is how kind of they work.
So, let's say if I just go to my VS code and just try to explain you need not to write
anything for now.
Let's say you can see that we are importing text and view from react native from next
chapter we are going to understand each of them.
So don't worry.
Let's say we have imported here view and we have imported here text we have two thing
make sense.
So, on iOS, let's say you are on iOS, so on iOS this view is going to be mapped towards
the UI view like that we have talked about like this is the native component.
So, you write for iOS you are using the same view, but internally they are going to map
towards UI view same for text and in same way let's say you are on Android and on Android
You have let's just say use this text so they are again mapped towards the text view, this
is a native component which is available to them.
So this mapping happens automatically.
You never, yes you never ever going to interact with this UI view with this text view or Android
views whatever is that directly.
So, I mean one of the biggest question that arises right now, why React Native uses this
approach?
So, this approach first of all give you like again a single code base, up second they give
you native look and feel, then they give you a good performance, yes they are very performant.
So, they give you good performance and a simple and consistent development experience.
So, this is what I am talking about.
They are going to give you a simple and consistent development experience.
So, you focus on building the UI using the core component and react native take care
of rendering native UI on each platform.
Perfect.
So, I hope so that makes sense.
So, if I just try to summarize you native component or platform specific component.
Perfect.
Like UI view, UI label, UI button.
If you are using shift Objective-C like view text view button, if you are using Java and
inside Java there is another way of writing it.
Like I don't exactly remember because I never written something inside Java.
Yeah, and in same way core component are react native components.
So this is what your core components.
This is why react native app feels truly native.
So from next chapter, we are going to start learning all of the core components that we
have, like we have view, we have text image, text input, pressable, scroll view, style
sheet, then button switch, a lot of things.
Perfect, so yeah this is pretty much it for this chapter and see you next time.