Alright everyone and welcome to the last chapter of this module, name as configure multiple
app variants.
So basically till now we know that how to create a development build for our entire application.
Alright now sometime let's say you wanted to have a multiple variations of your app.
One is for preview, one is for production and another one is for development.
So, in that case, you need to know about this configure multiple app variant.
You can definitely visit to this URL and start using it.
Alright, so, what is the first step for that always?
So, the first step you can see that like each variant require a unique Android application
ID.
And for iOS you need a unique bundle identifier to enable simulation, simul..
Alright, so what I can say is simultaneous, maybe I am wrong or right, installation on
one device.
So here is how IDs are set up in our application file.
We know that right now, if I come into here inside my application app.json,
So you will see for Android we have a package name as this and then we have a plugin and
all the other thing in same way for iOS right now we only have supported tablet but basically
what I'm talking about you can change this got it and you can decide the name of your
bundle identifier so that you can uniquely identify them.
So first thing first you just need
for creating the multiple bundle identifiers.
First of all, let me decrease the size of it.
All right.
And change the name of this, we can say app.json to something else.
So what is the name of that something else, which is app.config.js.
Right now we have app.json, but rename this.
this to app.
config.js or ts whatever you wanted to go with let's go with ts and the moment I open
it you will see still this is wrong this is not how you are basically going to use it.
First of all remove this curly braces from starting.
And this is the step number one and then what you need to do, you simply need to do here
export default and what I can do, I think I can just simply say export default and we
don't even need this export.
So also remove the last one.
All right.
And hopefully just give me a minute.
Let me just come into here and we don't if I just close this you will see this one.
So we don't need this expo and this last yes this one we don't need this even cool and
then simply say export default.
All right and the moment I say export default they are stop crying.
Perfect.
next and after export config you can simply coming to here.
And yes, do this and after this what you need to do, you just simply coming to here and
enclose all of them inside this, alright.
So basically we are just enclosing them inside a parenthesis.
So let me just do that in much better way, in much more understandable way.
So we first of all need this, yes.
Then we need here arrow.
and coming to here and at the very bottom add this very good now inside this export default we have access of
config
Perfect since we are using TypeScript so I can definitely add the types as well. So this is going to be config
context alright and
This is also going to be as as
expo
And let us move ahead and import both of the type from it.
So I can basically import this config context, let me show you from there, you can simply
say import config.
context and expo config from expo config exactly.
Alright, so now you will see this is how we wanted to go with it and the moment you format
this once you will see now this is formatted for myself as well and below this what you
will do you can simply spread this config here.
Perfect.
This is the step number one we need to do.
All right, perfect.
Now let's move ahead and what is the next step?
Next step is very simple.
So the next step is you can simply come into here and you will see update the dynamic values
based on the environment.
So simply copy this.
These are two variables.
So, the first one is isDev and another one is is_preview.
So first we have process.env.app variant which is development.
Same is preview when the value is going to be as preview.
Easy.
And after this, yes, you need to copy this.
What is this?
This is the get unique identifier of the name based on the, we can say, the build based
on the environment.
So if I save it, you will see if the this is div, then whatever the name of your application,
you wanted to put it.
So first of all.
This is the package name that I have.
So, first of all, let me copy this and also change this, change this as well and also
change this.
Cool.
Nice.
We will see.
If the development, if the identifier is in development mode, so this is the bundle identifier.
If we are in preview mode, this is the basically preview mode.
Alright, right now one of the biggest question that is arise, what do you mean by bundle
identifier?
So bundle identifier in iOS or in package name in Android, we can say this is a unique identifier.
Yes, this is a unique identifier for your application, whatever you are building that
distinguish it from all the other app in the world.
So this is we can say a unique ID for it.
Got it.
Like you know that your app have some we can say social security number kind of that permanent
ID card, a unique address in all of the app ecosystem.
So this is the format for it.
Unim.com your company name and the name of your application.
This is the basic format of Bundle Identifier.
got it, that's why we need it. So, COM is basically the commercial domain and then this
is your company and developer and the brand name and third one is your specific application
name. Perfect and why this is important, this is basically give you the uniqueness across
App Store and whenever you are putting some app updates then you need it. So, got it,
That is why we are doing this much of things.
Cool, I hope this is making sense now.
So if we are in development mode, this is our identifier.
If we are in preview mode, this is our identifier.
Otherwise, we are in production mode and this is the default, we can say identifier for
it.
Now how you can use it?
And this is how we are basically giving the name.
So name is definitely not the stickers mass.
The name is we can right now just go with module 10.
I know it's a bit weird name, but we are just understanding it right now.
Module 10.
Yes, no problem.
Perfect.
And in same way, now instead of going with this approach, you can simply call the get
app name.
Perfect.
This is how you can change it here.
In same way, you can also, we can say, let's keep the module as same.
Everything is going to be same.
Scheme is same.
Now, at this point, yes, we do not need the com dot, this is you will just simply call
this, this is basically going to give you a unique identifier of your application and
the moment I save it, we are good to go.
So, you can see that.
Again, if you're configuring this for iOS, this is what you need to do.
If you are doing this for Android, which we are doing right now, so you can see using
get unique identifier for package property and then configure your EAS JSON.
In EAS JSON, add the app variant environment variable.
So, let's move ahead and start adding them.
So let me go to my EAS JSON and inside this you will see this is all the environment we
have first one is the app development.
So inside development we have a property name as Env.
And inside this ENV we have app variant and what is that app variant that is a development
where it is defined it is defined here look at that app variant development cool whenever
we are in preview so what we need to do.
Simply coming to here and add app variant as preview and production need not to change
anything because by default production will come to this name.
Making sense?
I hope so.
Now, let's move ahead and try to create one more build.
Alright, again, this is going to take some time, but it's fine.
We are ready for it.
Let me close this application right now.
Clear everything and let's again build for development.
So ES build platform Android.
Yes, we are specifically building for Android and profile is going to be development and
let me hit this once again and let's see what we are going to get here.
slug for project identified extra.es project does not match the slug field in module 10
alright let me see how I can fix that so basically you can read this entire error and the error
is itself saying module - 10 does not match the slug field this module 10 so simply copy
this and I think I made some mistake and this.
Cool, I think this will work right now.
Hopefully, let's see.
Alright and then let's move ahead and try to rebuild this.
So AS build hyphen hyphen platform Android and again profile is development right now
and look at that.
Resolve the development environment for the build.
Perfect. And environment variable loaded from development build profile, which is with the
name of app variant, definitely generate a new key store. Yes, we need to create a new
key store because separately we are creating this one, one more APK got it. So definitely
let's wait for it and we'll see they are generating a key store in cloud created the key store
Compressing the project? Cool?
And again uploading to AIS build, our entire project is uploading to AIS build.
Perfect.
And after uploading this successfully, computed the project of fingerprint and yes, now our
build is in queue.
Let's just wait for a few minutes and then I'll be right back.
And yes, finally, we have installed it successfully, let me first of all say no.
And then let me click on this link and let me open this link here.
Alright and then let me press on install and let's just try to install this out.
Cool.
So, this is the variable, this is the basically QR code you need to install and simply scan
it, press over it.
And now you will find the install button.
Simply press over that and they have started installing.
Perfect.
So, let's just wait for a few seconds and then we'll see.
And I think we have installed it successfully.
So for that, let me go to my downloads and all right, we are still downloading it.
Cool.
So, definitely we can wait.
Alright, so now we have installed it and the moment I press on installation and now look
at the name of this.
So the name is coming as module 10 dev.
This is the beauty of it.
Perfect.
So how you can basically configure multiple app variations.
So, let's just wait for installation and again we haven't code anything.
So, you will don't see any difference between the code and nice we have installed it and
the moment I open it, definitely you will see something like this cool and I can definitely
start the development server one run dev.
What just happened?
Already 1x expose start, hopefully this will work now, yes and I can simply press on A.
So this is going look at that, open with, definitely we wanted to open with module 10
because they both are development build, that's why.
So simply say open module 10 dev, perfect.
And look at that amazing, amazing job.
This is how and if you just simply go to your home page, you will find two different app.
Definitely they both are development build, but in same way, you can have a preview build
as well and production build as well.
And this is your development build.
So you can definitely check all of them in the same application.
So, amazing, amazing job.
This is the end of our entire module named as AIS tutorial.
Definitely this is not completed yet, but the next part like AIS submit, AIS over the
top upload all of that features like AIS submit and AIS update.
We'll read about that whenever we go inside the production section.
So, right now we have a lot of project, lot more concept to understand, but this is pretty
much it and see you next time.